<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Quotables &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/category/quotables/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 03:06:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Verum cum vero non pugnat:  Maccovius, Voetius, &#038; Bavinck on philosophy and theology</title>
		<link>/journal/verum-cum-vero-non-pugnat-maccovius-voetius-bavinck-on-philosophy-and-theology/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 14:52:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed scholasticism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=1495</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[First, a few theses from Johannes Maccovius’s Theological and Philosophical Distinctions and Rules, ch. 1, On Holy Scripture: XXXVIII. The object of theology and the object of philosophy are diverse and distinct. XXXIX. Truth never runs counter to (pugno) truth. XL. Sound reason and theology do not conflict (pugno).1 Second, a thesis from Gisbertus Voetius’s &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/verum-cum-vero-non-pugnat-maccovius-voetius-bavinck-on-philosophy-and-theology/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Verum cum vero non pugnat:  Maccovius, Voetius, &#038; Bavinck on philosophy and theology"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>First, a few theses from Johannes Maccovius’s <em>Theological and Philosophical Distinctions and Rules</em>, ch. 1, On Holy Scripture:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  XXXVIII. The object of theology and the object of philosophy are diverse and distinct.</p>
<p>  XXXIX. Truth never runs counter to (pugno) truth.</p>
<p>  XL. Sound reason and theology do not conflict (pugno).<sup id="fnref-1495-1"><a href="#fn-1495-1" class="jetpack-footnote">1</a></sup>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Second, a thesis from Gisbertus Voetius’s Thersites, self-tormentor:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  I. The light of nature does not fight with (pugno) the light of grace, nor philosophy with theology. Therefore, a-theological, and also doing injury to God and His truth, are those who condemn philosophy.<sup id="fnref-1495-2"><a href="#fn-1495-2" class="jetpack-footnote">2</a></sup>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Third, a summation from Herman Bavinck’s <em>Reformed Dogmatics</em>, which employs the “non pugno” motif in Bavinck’s European narrative style:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  If theology thus has its internal principle not in faith as such but in believing reflection, the task of reason in theological science calls for further definition. In this context we must first of all and fundamentally reject the notion that regards faith and reason as two independent powers engaging in a life-and-death struggle with each other. . . . Faith, the faith by which we believe (de fides qua creditur), is not an organ or faculty next to or above reason but a disposition or habit of reason itself. . . . Faith, therefore, does not relieve Christians of the desire to study and reflect; rather it spurs them on to the end. Nature is not destroyed by regeneration but restored.</p>
<p>  Believers who want to devote themselves to the study of theology, accordingly, must prepare their minds for the task awaiting them. There is no admission to the temple of theology except by way of the study of the arts. Indispensable to the practitioner of the science of theology is philosophical, historical, and linguistic preparatory training.<sup id="fnref-1495-3"><a href="#fn-1495-3" class="jetpack-footnote">3</a></sup>
</p></blockquote>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn-1495-1">
<a href="https://archive.org/stream/ned-kbn-all-00003652-001#page/n44/mode/2up"><em>Distinctiones et regulae theologicae ac philosophicae</em></a> (1653), 20-21; translation from <a href="http://www.tua.nl/index.php?item=artikel&amp;paginaID=19&amp;artikelID=19"><em>Scholastic Discourse: Johannes Maccovius (1588–1644) on Theological and Philosophical Distinctions and Rules</em></a>, translated and edited by Willem J. van Asselt, Michael D. Bell, Gert van den Brink, Rein Ferwerda (Apeldoorn: Instituut voor Reformatieonderzoek, 2009), 78–81.&#160;<a href="#fnref-1495-1">&#8617;</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-1495-2">
<a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=ZIljAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA347#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true"><em>Thersites heautontimorumenos</em></a> (Utrecht : Ex Officinâ Abrahami ab Herwiick &amp; Hermanni Ribbii, 1635), 347; translation from Aza Goudriaan, <a href="http://www.brill.com/reformed-orthodoxy-and-philosophy-1625-1750"><em>Reformed Orthodoxy and Philosophy, 1625–1750: Gisbertus Voetius, Petrus Van Mastricht, and Anthonius Driessen</em></a>, Brill’s Series in Church History 26 (Brill, 2006), 30; cf. B. Hoon Woo, “<a href="https://www.academia.edu/3325870/_The_Understanding_of_Gisbertus_Voetius_and_Ren%C3%A9_Descartes_on_the_Relationship_of_Faith_and_Reason_and_Theology_and_Philosophy_Westminster_Theological_Journal_75_no._1_2013_45_63">‘The Understanding of Gisbertus Voetius and René Descartes on the Relationship of Faith and Reason, and Theology and Philosophy</a>,” <em>Westminster Theological Journal</em> 75, No. 1 (2013): 45–63; quote referenced at p. 54.&#160;<a href="#fnref-1495-2">&#8617;</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-1495-3">
Vol. 1, <em>Prolegomena</em>, trans. John Vriend, ed. John Bolt (Grand Rapids: Baker Academic, 2003), 616–17; Bavinck quotes Voetius&#8217;s disputations at 616n41; see also 618n46 for Bavinck’s short list of sources on the philosophy-theology relation, which includes the same disputations by Voetius.&#160;<a href="#fnref-1495-3">&#8617;</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>a prayer befitting the covenant of works</title>
		<link>/journal/a-prayer-befitting-the-covenant-of-works/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 15:54:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covenant theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed theology]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=1458</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[O Lord Jehovah, how little do we, poor miserable mortals, know of thy Supreme Deity, and incomprehensible perfections! . . . May the consciousness of our ignorance in other things kindle in our hearts an ineffable desire of that beatific vision, by which, knowing as we are known, we may in the abyss of thy infinity &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/a-prayer-befitting-the-covenant-of-works/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "a prayer befitting the covenant of works"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>O Lord Jehovah, how little do we, poor miserable mortals, know of thy Supreme Deity, and incomprehensible perfections! . . . May the consciousness of our ignorance in other things kindle in our hearts an ineffable desire of that beatific vision, by which, knowing as we are known, we may in the abyss of thy infinity behold those things which no thought of ours at present can reach!</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: right;">—<a href="http://www.prdl.org/author_view.php?a_id=91">Herman Witsius</a>, <em>The Economy of the Covenants</em>, ch. 4. <a href="https://archive.org/stream/MN41373ucmf_5#page/n75/mode/2up">sec. 23</a>.</p>
<p>Perhaps it is not far off to say that the health of one’s knowledge of the doctrine of the covenant is proportionate to an increase in such apropos prostrations before the Almighty and confessions of limitation.</p>
<p>Whether or not such a rule attains, this flavor of<em> theologia viatorum</em> is one to be desired.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sedeo, ergo sum</title>
		<link>/journal/sedeo-ergo-sum/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2016 20:15:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=1449</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We do not say with Descartes: “Cogito, ergo sum,” . . . ; on the contrary, instead of basing ourselves immediately upon the operation which is proper to the highest of our faculties, we rest first of all and with great assurance in the experience of touching, in which we have at the same time &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/sedeo-ergo-sum/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Sedeo, ergo sum"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>
  We do not say with Descartes: “Cogito, ergo sum,” . . . ; on the contrary, instead of basing ourselves immediately upon the operation which is proper to the highest of our faculties, we rest first of all and with great assurance in the experience of touching, in which we have at the same time an experience of existing. To be sure, this consciousness is not without thought, but it is a thought which depends upon touch and which does not as yet reveal itself as thought. It is the tangible qualities which are to us first principles of thought and action. If we had to venture an Aristotelian counterpart to Descartes’ “Cogito, ergo sum,” we would say without hesitation: “Sedeo, ergo sum”: I am sitting, therefore I am.
</p></blockquote>
<p><small>Charles De Koninck, “<a href="https://www.erudit.org/revue/ltp/1950/v6/n2/1019841ar.pdf">«Sedeo, Ergo Sum»: Considerations on the Touchstone of Certitude</a>,” <cite>Laval Théologique et Philosophique</cite> 6, no. 2 (1950): 343–48.</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Aquinas: the old woman’s faith vs. the philosophers’ reason</title>
		<link>/journal/aquinas-the-old-womans-faith-vs-the-philosophers-reason/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 20:24:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=1433</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[&#8220;The just man liveth by faith.&#8221; [Habakkuk 2:4] This is evident in that no one of the philosophers before the coming of Christ could, through his own powers, know God and the means necessary for salvation as well as any old woman since Christ’s coming knows Him through faith. Thomas Aquinas, Catechical Instructions of St. &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/aquinas-the-old-womans-faith-vs-the-philosophers-reason/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Aquinas: the old woman’s faith vs. the philosophers’ reason"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>
  &#8220;The just man liveth by faith.&#8221; [Habakkuk 2:4] This is evident in that no one of the philosophers before the coming of Christ could, through his own powers, know God and the means necessary for salvation as well as any old woman since Christ’s coming knows Him through faith.
</p></blockquote>
<p>Thomas Aquinas, <em>Catechical Instructions of St. Thomas Aquinas</em>, trans. Joseph B. Collins (Fort Collins, CO: Roman Catholic Books, 1939), 4.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Calling a spade</title>
		<link>/journal/calling-a-spade/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 21:54:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[morality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophia perennis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1404</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Significant advances can be made along the road of moral reformation by observing the simple expedient of calling a spade a spade. D. Q. McInerny, “Dishonest Language,” in Perennial Wisdom for Daily Life, vol. 1 (Elmhurst, PA: The Priestly Fraternity of Saint Peter, 2002), 6.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>
  Significant advances can be made along the road of moral reformation by observing the simple expedient of calling a spade a spade.
</p></blockquote>
<p>D. Q. McInerny, “Dishonest Language,” in <em>Perennial Wisdom for Daily Life</em>, vol. 1 (Elmhurst, PA: The Priestly Fraternity of Saint Peter, 2002), 6.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Goudriaan on Reformed philosophy</title>
		<link>/journal/goudriaan-on-reformed-philosophy/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2016 16:07:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed philosophy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1359</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dr. Aza Goudriaan’s (@Academia) essays are trenchant, weighty, and all-around top shelf in quality. Take, for instance, his foray with Irena Backus on the origin of the term “semipelagianism.”1 Or consider these substantial essays on the role of philosophy in the Reformed orthodox era: &#160; Aza Goudriaan, Reformed Orthodoxy and Philosophy, 1625–1750: Gisbertus Voetius, Petrus &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/goudriaan-on-reformed-philosophy/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Goudriaan on Reformed philosophy"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure id="attachment_1387" style="max-width: 132px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="http://www.godgeleerdheid.vu.nl/nl/over-de-faculteit/medewerkers/wetenschappelijk-personeel-g-l/goudriaan.aspx" rel="attachment wp-att-1387"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Aza_Goudriaan.jpg" alt="Dr. Aza Goudriaan" width="132" height="165" class="size-full wp-image-1387" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Aza Goudriaan</figcaption></figure><a href="https://vu-nl.academia.edu/AzaGoudriaan">Dr. Aza Goudriaan’s</a> <small>(<a href="https://vu-nl.academia.edu/AzaGoudriaan">@Academia</a>)</small> essays are trenchant, weighty, and all-around top shelf in quality. Take, for instance, his foray with Irena Backus on <a href="https://www.academia.edu/5515119/Semipelagianism_The_Origins_of_the_Term_and_its_Passage_into_the_History_of_Heresy">the origin of the term “semipelagianism.”</a><sup id="fnref-1359-1"><a href="#fn-1359-1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Or consider these substantial essays on the role of philosophy in the Reformed orthodox era:</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.brill.com/reformed-orthodoxy-and-philosophy-1625-1750" rel="attachment wp-att-1383"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Goudriaan_ReformedOrthodoxyAndPhilosophy.jpg" alt="Reformed Orthodoxy and Philosophy, 1625–1750: Gisbertus Voetius, Petrus van Mastricht, and Anthonius Driessen — by Aza Goudriaan" width="195" height="292" class="alignright size-full wp-image-1383" /></a> Aza Goudriaan, <a href="http://www.brill.com/reformed-orthodoxy-and-philosophy-1625-1750"><em>Reformed Orthodoxy and Philosophy, 1625–1750: Gisbertus Voetius, Petrus Van Mastricht, and Anthonius Driessen</em></a>, Brill’s Series in Church History 26 (Leiden: Brill, 2006).</li>
<li>Aza Goudriaan, “Ulrik Huber (1636–1694) and John Calvin: The Franeker Debate on Human Reason and the Bible (1686–1687),” <em>Church History and Religious Culture</em> 91, no. 1 (2011): 165–78.</li>
<li>Aza Goudriaan, “Theology and Philosophy,” in <em>A Companion to Reformed Orthodoxy</em>, ed. Herman J. Selderhuis (Leiden: Brill, 2013), 27–63.</li>
</ol>
<p>For whetting one’s appetite, several points in the conclusion of the “Theology and Philosophy” essay are worth considering in the American Reformed and Presbyterian orb. First and foremost:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  Early modem Reformed thinkers did not spurn philosophy in itself. None of the different philosophical orientations articulated during the early modem period seems to have rejected philosophical or natural<br />
  theology as such. In this period there was no such phenomenon as, in the words of a prominent present-day Reformed philosopher, “The Reformed Objection to Natural Theology.” Modern Reformed conceptions, such as those of Barthian theology or of the school of reformational philosophy, differ starkly in their attitude towards natural theology from mainstream seventeenth-century Reformed theology. The latter&#8217;s largely positive reception of proofs for God’s existence clearly demonstrates its evidentialist orientation. <small>(pp. 61–62)</small>
</p></blockquote>
<p>He continues with an observation on the eclecticism of Reformed philosophy in the early modern era, an eclecticism that did not devolve into sheer pluralism and that maintained commitments to biblical authority and the unity of truth in the <em>duplex ordo cognitionis</em><sup id="fnref-1359-2"><a href="#fn-1359-2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  The philosophy that the Reformed adopted was not a single monolithic set of thoughts. Reformed thinkers philosophized in a number of different, sometimes diametrically opposed, ways. Quite a few were Ramists, many opted for an eclectic form of Christian Aristotelianism, while yet others supported Cartesian philosophy and attempted to articulate Reformed theology in terms of Cartesian concepts and presuppositions. Reformed doctrine was obviously taken to be compatible with a number of different philosophical approaches.</p>
<p>  This is not to say that all philosophical orientations were equally compatible with biblical Christianity. In some important respects, Aristotelian eclecticism was able to support biblical exegesis better than Cartesianism was—here one could think of its basic empirical orientation and of the form-matter concepts. The same seems to be true of the Aristotelians’ subordination of natural reason to theology in comparison to the strict separation between theology and philosophy advocated by some Cartesians. It could be argued that the latter separation contributed to a secularization of philosophy which, on the supposition of the unity of truth and its basic knowability, could only lead to an increasing antagonism between philosophy and theology. <small>(p. 62, paragraph break added)</small>
</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn-1359-1">
Irena Backus and Aza Goudriaan, “‘Semipelagianism’: The Origins of the Term and Its Passage into the History of Heresy,” <em>Journal of Ecclesiastical History</em> 65, no. 1 (2014): 25–46.&#160;<a href="#fnref-1359-1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-1359-2">
This mouthful of a term, see Richard A. Muller, “‘Duplex Cognitio Dei’ in the Theology of Early Reformed Orthodoxy,” <em>Sixteenth Century Journal</em> 10, no. 2 (Summer 1979): 51–62; Romanus Cessario OP, “<a href="http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_academies/san-tommaso/publications/dc2.pdf#page=53">Duplex Ordo Cognitionis</a>,” Doctor Communis 2 n.s. (2002): 102–9; Eduardo J. Echeverria, <em><a href="http://www.brill.com/berkouwer-and-catholicism">Berkouwer and Catholicism: Disputed Questions</a></em>, Studies in Reformed Theology 24 (Leiden: Brill, 2013).&#160;<a href="#fnref-1359-2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>cor legis naturalis</title>
		<link>/journal/cor-legis-naturalis/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 20:11:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theologia naturalis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed orthodoxy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1353</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[. . . it is imperative for Christians to reaffirm their conviction that God has made the world objectively meaningful and purposeful and that he made human beings capable of discovering this meaning and purpose, despite their sinful propensity to distort what they discover. This, it seems to me, gets to the heart of what, &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/cor-legis-naturalis/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "cor legis naturalis"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>
  . . . it is imperative for Christians to reaffirm their conviction that God has made the world objectively meaningful and purposeful and that he made human beings capable of discovering this meaning and purpose, despite their sinful propensity to distort what they discover. This, it seems to me, gets to the heart of what, historically, Christian natural law theory is all about.</p>
<p>  Natural law, in other words, is not first and foremost a means for making moral or apologetic arguments to which unbelievers will be compelled to give assent, but a means by which Christians express their conviction that God has made this universe in such a manner that there is a morally appropriate way for human beings to live within it, and that, furthermore, the moral law God has explicitly revealed in Scripture is not arbitrary but a reflection of this created reality. The Reformed community’s recent suspicion of natural law theory, I fear, has weakened its theological ability to affirm these things in a coherent and powerful way.
</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: right; font-size:.8em;">— <a href="https://www.wscal.edu/academics/faculty/david-m-vandrunen">David VanDrunen</a>, “Natural Law for Reformed Theology,”<br /><cite>Journal of Reformed Theology</cite> 9, no. 2 (2015): 120.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Olgiati on the synthetic whole</title>
		<link>/journal/olgiati-on-the-synthetic-whole/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 15:04:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Herman Bavinck]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed dogmatics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1333</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Pondering Bavinck’s outline of his Dogmatiek brought to mind a passage in the introduction to Francesco Olgiati’s The Key to the Study of St. Thomas:1 In the greater part of these recent works on St. Thomas Auinas one notes a preference for the analytic method. To be sure, this method had its merits. It was &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/olgiati-on-the-synthetic-whole/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Olgiati on the synthetic whole"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure id="attachment_1335" style="max-width: 177px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="http://it.cathopedia.org/wiki/Francesco_Olgiati" rel="attachment wp-att-1335"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Olgiati-e1455746472172.jpg" alt="Francesco Olgiati (1886–1962) " width="177" height="238" class="size-full wp-image-1335" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Francesco Olgiati<br />(1886–1962)</figcaption></figure>Pondering <a href="/bavincks-outline-of-the-reformed-dogmatics/">Bavinck’s outline</a> of his <em>Dogmatiek</em> brought to mind a passage in the introduction to Francesco Olgiati’s <em>The Key to the Study of St. Thomas</em>:<sup id="fnref-1333-1"><a href="#fn-1333-1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>
<blockquote><p>
  In the greater part of these recent works on St. Thomas Auinas one notes a preference for the analytic method. To be sure, this method had its merits. It was necessary to call attention to the theses, the theories, the several parts of the system, just as when seeking to make a person known, we begin by describing his life with its most noteworthy facts and salient exploits, as well as its most minute episodes and many seemingly negligible details. Every point of the Thomistic conception is scrutinized, illumined, discussed. After the manner of hardy explorers, the students of St. Thomas, in their loving solicitude to trace its lines with due precision, have not overlooked a single outskirt of this hallowed ground.
</p></blockquote>
<p>Olgiati then proceeds to describe the synthetic method of which his trenchant <em>Key</em> elucidates as a case in point:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  Hitherto, however, the synthetic method has not received the attention it deserves. It would seem that after the painstaking and valuable researches along the way of analysis, not enough stress has been laid on pointing out to the men of our age the wonderful unity of the whole system. Frequently, even in otherwise eminent and learned works, the manifold doctrines engross the reader’s attention without making him feel the beauty and vibration of the one and only spirit that breathes life into the whole. So it happens that many, especially among its opponents, imagine they have understood Thomism, [all] the while as a matter of fact the <em>soul</em> of St. Thomas eludes their grasp. (pp. iv–v)
</p></blockquote>
<p>The power of the sapiential approach is not in its manifold distinctions but in its striving toward synthesis; to the analytic “he who distinguishes well learns well” must be added the synthetic “distinguish to unite” if one is to penetrate “the wonderful unity of the whole system.”</p>
<p>Why? The metaphysician moves from the appearances of things to their essences, from <em>ens</em> to <em>ratio entis</em>, from participated beings to First Being, from effects to First (and Final) Cause.<sup id="fnref-1333-2"><a href="#fn-1333-2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> The theologian moves from the <em>logoi</em> of Holy Scripture to the <em>Logos</em>, from revelation deposited to revelation cogitated, from tenets of faith scattered to a body of divinity. Both perform unitive cognitive acts, referring all things to their chief and highest ends. Rarely is one person gifted with the extraordinary grace, genius, and wisdom required to perform both unitive acts in a preeminent degree. Such is the case with the <em>doctor communis</em>.</p>
<p>And such is the case too in its own way with the neo-Calvinist lights such as Kuyper and Bavinck and their intellectual forebearers, the Reformed orthodox doctors, as is slowly being recognized in contemporary Reformed Protestantism. To speculate for a minute in this digression, if someone ventured a similar synthetic study either of Bavinck’s <em>Dogmatiek</em> in particular or of Reformed dogmatics in general, I wonder whether the answer to “What is the Key?” would be similar to Olgiati’s answer with respect to Thomas.</p>
<p>Whatever the case, it seems desirable that we scholars in the field of systematic theology would every now and then take leave of the unending stream of analytic studies and pose to ourselves the synthetic questions lest we be found mistaking parts of the body for the soul, or, what might be worse, forgetting that there is a soul in our field to be found.</p>
<p>Along this line the outline of Bavinck&#8217;s <em>Dogmatics</em> provides a small opportunity to apply a synthetic <em>formalgegenstand</em> and to taste the “wonderful unity.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn-1333-1">
Trans. John S. Zybura, 2nd ed. (St. Louis: Herder, 1929).&#160;<a href="#fnref-1333-1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-1333-2">
On the unity of first and final cause, see 1. Duane H. Berquist, “<a href="http://www.aristotle-aquinas.org/peripatetikos-8/">The Truth of Aristotle’s Theology</a>,” <em>Peripatetikos</em> 8 (2011): 45–69.&#160;<a href="#fnref-1333-2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Voetius on metaphysics</title>
		<link>/journal/voetius-on-metaphysics/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 02:33:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed scholasticism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1302</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[&#8230;a theologian is no more able to forego metaphysics and logic than a carpenter a hammer or a soldier weapons. Gisbertus Voetius, Exercitia et bibliotheca studiosi theologiae, 2nd ed. (Utrecht, 1651), 26; cf. Aza Goudriaan, “Theology and Philosophy,” in A Companion to Reformed Orthodoxy, ed. Herman J. Selderhuis (Leiden: Brill, 2013), 27–63 (translation at p. 33; altered). &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/voetius-on-metaphysics/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Voetius on metaphysics"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<figure id="attachment_1306" style="max-width: 150px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="http://www.prdl.org/author_view.php?a_id=68" rel="attachment wp-att-1306"><img class="wp-image-1306 size-thumbnail" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Voetius-150x150.jpg" alt="Gisbertus Voetius (1589–1676)" width="150" height="150" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Gisbertus Voetius (1589–1676)</figcaption></figure>
<p>&#8230;a theologian is no more able to forego metaphysics and logic than a carpenter a hammer or a soldier weapons.</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left; font-size: .8em;">Gisbertus Voetius, <em><a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=KxYVAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA26#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">Exercitia et bibliotheca studiosi theologiae</a></em>, 2nd ed. (Utrecht, 1651), 26; cf. Aza Goudriaan, “Theology and Philosophy,” in <em>A Companion to Reformed Orthodoxy</em>, ed. Herman J. Selderhuis (Leiden: Brill, 2013), 27–63 (translation at p. 33; altered). Full sentence: <em>Ad accuratos, distinctos, &amp; evidentes conceptus tam anascevastice quam catascevastice in Theologia dogmatica &amp; practica, adhaec in explicatione scriptura formandos, ad proprias meditationes ampliandas, &amp; ad alienas diiudicandas non magis metaphysica &amp; logica carere potest Theologus quam faber malleo, aut miles armis.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Steinmetz: “What Luther Got Wrong” about Aquinas</title>
		<link>/journal/steinmetz-what-luther-got-wrong-about-aquinas/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 23:02:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Martin Luther]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Protestant scholasticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1277</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It would be too much to assume that Aquinas will ever be as central a theologian for Protestants as he has been for Catholics. But Protestants have begun to put an end to their own self-imposed impoverishment. They have opened the ranks of the theologians with whom they are in regular conversation to include Aquinas. &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/steinmetz-what-luther-got-wrong-about-aquinas/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Steinmetz: “What Luther Got Wrong” about Aquinas"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><a href="http://divinity.duke.edu/academics/faculty/david-steinmetz"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-1278" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/DavidSteinmetz.jpg" alt="DavidSteinmetz" width="90" height="120" /></a>It would be too much to assume that Aquinas will ever be as central a theologian for Protestants as he has been for Catholics. But Protestants have begun to put an end to their own self-imposed impoverishment. They have opened the ranks of the theologians with whom they are in regular conversation to include Aquinas. It is a development long overdue.</p></blockquote>
<p>—Professor Emeritus David C. Steinmetz, “<a href="http://www.religion-online.org/showarticle.asp?title=3267">What Luther Got Wrong</a>” (repr. from <em>Christian Century</em>, August 23, 2005, pp. 23, 25)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
