<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>natural revelation &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/natural-revelation/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 03:06:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A Westminster Divine on Faith and Reason</title>
		<link>/journal/westminster-divine-faith-reason/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2014 21:22:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural revelation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reason]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=588</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[One underappreciated feature of the Westminster divines is that they not only wrote in multiple theological genres (i.e., Scripture commentaries, catechisms, disputations, bodies of divinity) but also wrote in multiple philosophical or non-theological genres. Edward Reynolds’s (1599–1676) Treatise on the Passions and Faculties of the Soul (1640) is one such example of the latter. In thinking about the &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/westminster-divine-faith-reason/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "A Westminster Divine on Faith and Reason"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.prdl.org/author_view.php?a_id=473"><img class="alignleft wp-image-589 size-medium" style="border: 1px solid black;" title="Edward Reynolds (1599–1676)" src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/Edward_Reynolds-192x300.jpg" alt="NPG D5802,Edward Reynolds,by David Loggan" width="192" height="300" /></a>One underappreciated feature of the Westminster divines is that they not only wrote in multiple theological genres (i.e., Scripture commentaries, catechisms, disputations, bodies of divinity) but also wrote in multiple philosophical or non-theological genres. <a title="View the Edward Reynolds entry at the Post-Reformation Digital Library" href="http://www.prdl.org/author_view.php?a_id=473">Edward Reynolds’s</a> (1599–1676) <em>Treatise on the Passions and Faculties of the Soul</em> (1640) is one such example of the latter.</p>
<p>In thinking about the relation of faith and reason it is instructive to follow the brief rationale he gives in <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=NjsQAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">the preface</a> for why a theologian like himself would venture to write a philosophical work. First, he gives biblical reasons to show that God himself in Holy Scripture has bestowed honor on humanity’s natural knowledge in many ways such as in God’s bringing the animals to Adam so that he would name them.</p>
<p>Second, he points to the “ancient Christian churches,” noting that church fathers from Clement to John of Damascus have “not denied unto the world their philosophical and poetical labours, either whole and alone, or mixed and directed to theological ends” (5).</p>
<p>Third, he notes notes that the Protestant doctors followed the same practice as the church fathers and medieval scholastics and produces a wide array of philosophical works:</p>
<blockquote><p>besides the schoolmen, and those vast labours of many of that side in dialectical, physical, and metaphysical writings, we might instance in very many of the reformed churches abroad, some of whose younger labours have seen the light: as also in the oratory, logical, moral, historical, mathematical, miscellaneous writings of many learned divines of our own church. . . . (6)</p></blockquote>
<p>Fourth, he gives his own terse walk down the well-worn path regarding the subordination of natural to supernatural knowledge, the necessity of natural knowledge for interpreting Holy Scripture, the spoils of Egypt motif found throughout the Old and New Testaments, and warnings regarding not the use but the misuse of philosophy. At one memorable point along this path Edwards remarks:</p>
<blockquote><p>when I consider that the spoils of Egypt were by God allowed to enrich Israel, and the spoils of the Gentiles reserved by David for the building of the temple; that a Gentile, by legal purification and marriage, might become an Israelite; that the crown of Rabbah was put upon the head of David, and the sword of Goliath used to slay himself; that the gold, and myrrh, and frankincense of the Wise men of the East, was offered unto the Christ; when I find the apostle convincing the Jews out of their law, and the philosophers out of their maxims; and every gift, as well as every creature of God, is good, and may be sanctified for the use and delight of man;  I then conclude with myself, that the moral and philosophical glass of the human soul may be of some service even unto the tabernacle, as the looking-glasses of the Israelitish women were unto the altar. (6–7)</p></blockquote>
<p>Both the method and content of the argument displayed in this brief preface—perhaps commonplace in its own time—is worthy of consideration and even emulation in our time, a time in which such wisdom and Reformed catholicity is not so common.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
