<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>missiology &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/missiology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 23:01:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Père Etienne Renaud</title>
		<link>/journal/pere-etienne-renaud/</link>
		<comments>/journal/pere-etienne-renaud/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2013 14:58:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian-Muslim relations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith dialog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[missiology]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=327</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Daniel Martin Varisco’s moving, three-part memoriam (1, 2, 3) for his recently deceased friend, Père Etienne Renaud, includes Renaud’s pastoral letter concerning Christian-Muslim dialog. Born out of his experience as a Christian missionary to Muslims in West Africa, this letter is worthy of pondering insofar as it is full of the expensive sort of wisdom won by lifelong commitment &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/pere-etienne-renaud/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Père Etienne Renaud"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://peres-blancs.cef.fr/etienne_renaud.htm"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-328" alt="Etienne Renaud" src="https://dash.dedeo.tk/wp-content/uploads/etienne_renaud.jpg" width="200" height="286" /></a>Daniel Martin Varisco’s moving, three-part memoriam (<a href="http://tabsir.net/?p=2220">1</a>, <a href="http://tabsir.net/?p=2221">2</a>, <a href="http://tabsir.net/?p=2222">3</a>) for his recently deceased friend, Père Etienne Renaud, includes Renaud’s <a href="http://tabsir.net/?p=2221">pastoral letter concerning Christian-Muslim dialog</a>. Born out of his experience as a Christian missionary to Muslims in West Africa, this letter is worthy of pondering insofar as it is full of the expensive sort of wisdom won by lifelong commitment to deep, loving, and real engagement with Muslims.</p>
<p>Consider Renaud’s take on Christian-Muslim dialog:</p>
<blockquote><p>True dialogue, the one in which you are wholly committed with all that you “are” can but be witness, and hence mission. The important thing is to promote with every man a true encounter, which will be both dialogue and mission at the same time. A Tunisian Professor, Mohammed Talbi, speaks of a mutual “duty of apostolate.” Since the truth of the encounter implies that at the end, each one should be able to state his inmost convictions with complete frankness. It is an ideal rarely achieved, rarely possible even, but towards which we must always tend, and which proceeds through absolute respect for one’s interlocutor.</p></blockquote>
<p>His comment on avoiding the easy temptation to abstract “Islam” from concrete relationships with Muslims is as insightful as it is apropos, perhaps especially so among Western Christians:</p>
<blockquote><p>It is essential to remind ourselves that Islam does not have only one single face and we need to guard against making global judgments, a sign that we have few contacts with people in the concrete things of their life.</p></blockquote>
<p>Finally, his encouragement to walk the gospel’s “knife edge” fosters a healthy, realistic missiological perspective on Islam over against idealistic dreams or skeptical rants:</p>
<blockquote><p>In this we must not be naïve or nurse any illusions, underestimating the difficulties of the encounter. I believe on the contrary that we need to look them straight in the face and that irenicism does not pay. But on the other hand, let us take care not to sink into scepticism and cynicism. The Gospel invites us to remain on a knife-edge: “Wise as serpents and innocent as doves.” To be both realistic and evangelical at the same time: two words which apparently are opposed to one another, but isn’t the Gospel a realism of a higher order, the only one which lasts from the viewpoint of eternity?</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/journal/pere-etienne-renaud/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Fatiha Kaouès on Evangelical Missions in the Muslim World</title>
		<link>/journal/fatiha-kaoues-on-evangelical-missions-in-the-muslim-world/</link>
		<comments>/journal/fatiha-kaoues-on-evangelical-missions-in-the-muslim-world/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 18:01:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evangelism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[missiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[missions]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=162</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Religioscope’s interview with Fatiha Kaouès is worth reading for a local, historical perspective on Evangelical missions in Egypt and Lebanon, a story in which British imperialism, American missiology, and Arab nationalism play a large role. For instance, her remark about the house church model being the most predominant current form of Protestant evangelism is interesting to &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/fatiha-kaoues-on-evangelical-missions-in-the-muslim-world/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Fatiha Kaouès on Evangelical Missions in the Muslim World"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://goo.gl/oEvPb"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-163" alt="Religioscope Interview" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/Religioscope_interview.jpg" width="200" height="274" /></a><a href="http://goo.gl/oEvPb"><em>Religioscope’s</em> interview with Fatiha Kaouès</a> is worth reading for a local, historical perspective on Evangelical missions in Egypt and Lebanon, a story in which British imperialism, American missiology, and Arab nationalism play a large role.</p>
<p>For instance, her remark about the house church model being the most predominant current form of Protestant evangelism is interesting to reflect upon in my American Presbyterian context given that:</p>
<ul>
<li>the house church movement is largely dismissed in Reformed ecclesiology,</li>
<li>and Reformed leaders don’t seem to have vibrant strategies for Muslim evangelism in the American context.</li>
</ul>
<p>From what I could gather in preparations for my class last fall, not many Reformed churches have Muslim outreaches of any kind. And when I asked Reformed pastors and leaders about how to reach Muslims in America with the gospel, the basic answer I received all around was, “one-on-one relationships.” Does this mean, then, that older strategies such as the “meetings for better understanding” approach or public debates (to bring up the elenctic side of things) are dead or passé? Is this answer truly the best contemporary wisdom, or is it a resignation that we American Evangelicals aren’t doing much of <em>anything </em>to open our hearts to our American Muslim neighbors? I’m not yet sure.</p>
<p>Further, that these Egyptian house churches have discipleship programs for MBBs brings up a topic that deserves further attention in Reformed churches: discipleship (or “catechism,” to use the older word) specifically geared toward MBBs is, from what I have gathered thus far, virtually non-existent in Reformed churches. Yet, in my view, Reformed churches have a rich, catholic theological heritage that could be a great boon to MBB catechumens (and catechists!) on topics such as Nicene trinitarianism, Chalcedonian Christology, the divine decrees, human free will, and covenant theology, all of which have parallels/touch points/reinterpretations in Islamic theology. Will the Lord raise up harvesters in this field?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/journal/fatiha-kaoues-on-evangelical-missions-in-the-muslim-world/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
