<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Seminary &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/seminary/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 03:06:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The five stages of CTS PhD comprehensives (part 1)</title>
		<link>/journal/the-five-stages-of-cts-phd-comprehensives-part-1/</link>
		<comments>/journal/the-five-stages-of-cts-phd-comprehensives-part-1/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2015 02:14:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[phd]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seminary]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1287</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Round 1: before the handwritten exams Denial: “I have plenty of time. I will enjoy this year. . . .” [spoken to self gleefully] Anger: “whaaaat!” upon receiving the 26-page reading list Bargaining: “Wait, maybe I still got this: I’ll use my expertly-honed skimming skills—one, two, skip a few” (after actually perusing said list a month or three later) Depression: the conflicted “oh snap, &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/the-five-stages-of-cts-phd-comprehensives-part-1/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "The five stages of CTS PhD comprehensives (part 1)"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Round 1: before the handwritten exams</h3>
<ol>
<li>Denial: “I have <em>plenty</em> of time. I will enjoy this year. . . .” [spoken to self gleefully]</li>
<li>Anger: “whaaaat!” upon receiving the <em>26-page</em> reading list</li>
<li>Bargaining: “Wait, maybe I still got this: I’ll use my expertly-honed skimming skills—one, two, skip a few” (after actually perusing said list a month or three later)</li>
<li>Depression: the conflicted “oh snap, I don’t got this” that spontaneously occurs after realizing how long it took to read the first item in first section of said list and how hard it is to skim any work entitled <em>Summa</em> or any book authored by a Puritan or Karl Barth.</li>
<li>Acceptance: revives motto from the previous two years of coursework: “I’ll sleep <em>after</em> my PhD. . . .”</li>
</ol>
<p>[9 months of zombie life intervene, the kind that is not in any way induced from binge watching The Walking Dead]</p>
<h3>Round 2: at the handwritten exams</h3>
<ol>
<li>Denial: “Five hours to write is <em>plenty</em> of time. I know everything; I got this. . . .”</li>
<li>Anger: ordinarily there is a fourfold actuality: first, upon realizing that the quantity and scope of the questions seems more fitting for a being hailing from the supernatural rather than the natural order; second, upon realizing that the “one, two, skip a few” method for parsing the reading list referenced above has resulted in a possible apophatic downside of the non-mysterious, non-worship-inducing variety; third, realizing that the first question just took 1.75 hrs to answer and that there are five more to go (tic tock); fourth, realizing how much one’s writing hand hurts since one has not handwritten anything longer than a thank you note in over a decade.</li>
<li>Bargaining: “I’ll skip that one for now, and it will look easier when I come back to it later. . . .”</li>
<li>Depression: the effect of said bargaining, the potency of which is proportionate to the now-setting-in realization that there are four more of these delightful five-hour sessions after this one.</li>
<li>Acceptance: “I’ll get to do this to <em>my</em> students some day. It will be worth it. Mwah hah hah.”</li>
</ol>
<p>[furious, spirited, truly inspired writing intervenes through very the last minute of the five-hour session; repeated fivefold]</p>
<h3>Round 3: typing up the handwritten exams</h3>
<ol>
<li>Denial: “Twenty-four hours to submit is <em>plenty</em> of time, and my answers are probably better than I first thought. I love bluebook exams in the digital age: they’re ancient-future hip and all that jazz. . . .”</li>
<li>Anger: ordinarily there is a fourfold actuality: first, upon realizing that one has just woken up after sleeping for nearly 23 hours straight and concomitantly realizing with great surprise that even zombies need a bi-annual sleep; second, upon realizing that neither the quality of one’s handwriting nor the quality of one’s answers have improved after sleeping on it; third, realizing as you’re reading how much you forgot to say in that answer, and that one, and . . . ; fourth, the five, or five-hundred “wait, <em>what</em>? I wrote <em>that</em>?” moments.</li>
<li>Bargaining: “If I choose a professional serif font and make the formatting extra nice, my answers will appear better.” [Enters typesetting hero mode. Perfect Chicago Manual of Style achieved.]</li>
<li>Depression: realizes that an improvement in the order of aesthetics does not entail an improvement in the order of cognition.</li>
<li>Acceptance: “I’ll feel better if I roll like Pilate in John 19:22. . . .” Attachment sent. [Metaphorically washes hands.]</li>
</ol>
<p>[after the fifth iteration of round three, momentary emerges from zombie cave and attempts to resume normal human functioning: remembers that he’s married; realises that his children are nine-months-worth larger-sized than he last saw them (i.e., before encountering “the list”); realizes that he might not remain married if he forgets anniversary one more time or attempts any further exams (postdoc? <em>non esse</em>—that’s not even <em>esse in potentia</em>—as far as wife is concerned); sleeps slightly more frequently than bi-annually]</p>
<p>To be continued. . . .</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/journal/the-five-stages-of-cts-phd-comprehensives-part-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Locus de Deo: the lifeblood and heart of sacred doctrine</title>
		<link>/journal/the-lifeblood-and-heart-of-sacred-doctrine/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2015 15:07:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[God]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seminary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=938</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[If mystery is the lifeblood of dogmatics (HT: Bavinck), it is because God is its very life and heart. Thomas Aquinas well summarizes the classical teaching on the heart/object of theology: But sacred doctrine is chiefly concerned with God. . . .1 And again: . . . the chief aim of sacred doctrine is to teach the knowledge &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/the-lifeblood-and-heart-of-sacred-doctrine/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Locus de Deo: the lifeblood and heart of sacred doctrine"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If mystery is the lifeblood of dogmatics (HT: Bavinck), it is because God is its very life and heart.</p>
<p>Thomas Aquinas well summarizes the classical teaching on the heart/object of theology:</p>
<blockquote><p>But sacred doctrine is chiefly concerned with God. . . .<sup>1</sup></p></blockquote>
<p>And again:</p>
<blockquote><p>. . . the chief aim of sacred doctrine is to teach the knowledge of God, not only as He is in Himself, but also as He is the beginning of things and their last end, and especially of rational creatures. . . .<sup>2</sup></p></blockquote>
<p>The Protestant doctors in the period of Reformed orthodoxy appropriated this catholic wisdom concerning the <em>locus de Deo. </em>For instance, Francis Turretin (1623–1687) writes concerning the object of sacred doctrine that:</p>
<blockquote><p>the more common and true opinion is that of those who refer it to God and divine things. . . . Thus that all things are discussed in theology either because they deal with God himself or have a relation (<em>schesin</em>) to him as the first principle and ultimate end.<sup>3</sup></p></blockquote>
<p>Additionally, the <a href="http://www.reformation21.org/articles/synopsis-purioris-theologiae.php">Leiden Synopsis</a> exclaims regarding the role of the locus de Deo in “most-sacred theology” that:</p>
<blockquote><p>God is treated not only as the principle upon which it is constructed and the source of our knowledge of it but also as the subject and the foremost, primary (<em>primus ac primarius</em>) <em>locus</em> of Theology from which all the others flow forth, by which they are held together, and to which they should be directed.<sup>4</sup></p></blockquote>
<p>Herman Bavinck (1854–1921), perhaps one of the last of the modern Protestant doctors who operated unapologetically within the tradition of Protestant orthodoxy, expresses this same commitment in the introduction to his treatment of the doctrine of God:</p>
<blockquote><p>In truth, the knowledge that God has revealed of himself in nature and Scripture far surpasses human imagination and understanding. In that sense it is all mystery with which the science of dogmatics is concerned, for it does not deal with finite creatures, but from beginning to end looks past all creatures and focuses on the eternal and infinite One himself. From the very start of its labors, it faces the incomprehensible One. From him it derives its inception, for from him are all things. But also in the remaining loci, when it turns its attention to creatures, it views them only in relation to God as they exist from him and through him and for him [Rom. 11:36].</p>
<p>So then, the knowledge of God is the only dogma, the exclusive content, of the entire field of dogmatics. All the doctrines treated in dogmatics—whether they concern the universe, humanity, Christ, and so forth—are but the explication of the one central dogma of the knowledge of God. All things are considered in light of God, subsumed under him, traced back to him as the starting point. Dogmatics is always called upon to ponder and describe God and God alone, whose glory is in creation and re-creation, in nature and grace, in the world and in the church. It is the knowledge of him alone that dogmatics must put on display.<sup>5</sup></p></blockquote>
<p>I dig the classical dictum concerning theology that flows out of this perennial teaching: theology is taught by God, teaches God, and leads to God. Yet my experience reveals a discouragingly high failure rate at keeping my eyes aimed on this end even, ironically, amidst the very act of post-graduate study <em>of theology</em>.</p>
<p>In listening to my own <em>theologoi</em> and those of others, I am forced to conclude that the more one’s theological discourse loses sight of its true object (which, BTW, is the ever-present danger, strong temptation, and intense gravity under which all seminary students and teachers labor in the present evil age), the less of the divine mystery one tastes at the Lord’s table, sees in the Lord’s Word, senses in the Lord’s house, finds in the communion of the saints, and expresses in well-ordered theological words whether printed on the page or spoken in the lectern. Without the beating heart, the lifeblood is cold, static, dead.</p>
<p>But to dig even deeper here, albeit too briefly, if I&#8217;m honest with myself I see in my heart—that chamber of the most intimate, private theological discourse—that when my eyes droop, when in my “theologizing” I replace the object of theology with lesser objects that at the time seemed for whatever foolish reason greater than The Only Object (things like proving my view of such and such superior to another’s or chasing one of the million rabbit trails to which my own curiosity leads or any other of the human vices that love to express themselves in academic study), my prayers either cease or hit the ceiling. They cease and/or they turn into meaningless platitudes: Lord help my kids, Lord give me this or that, blah blah. In these moments my “prayers” seem to become my conscience’s object lesson on the fact that the lifeblood has gone cold not only in my theology but in my heart.</p>
<p>Perhaps this is one of the reasons for the existence of re-orienting, gaze-lifting preparatory exercises such as the <a href="/journal/quotables/a-prayer-before-study/">student’s prayer</a>, preparation guidelines for Sabbath worship and communion given in the Reformed confessions, and the like. These humble things are wise prods for keeping theology’s main thing the main thing, which is much easier said than done even in doing theology.</p>
<h4>Notes</h4>
<p><small>1. <em>Sacra autem doctrina est principaliter de Deo.</em> Aquinas, <em>ST</em> <a href="http://dhspriory.org/thomas/summa/FP/FP001.html#FPQ1A4THEP1">1.1.4</a> sed contra.</small></p>
<p><small><em>2. Quia igitur principalis intentio huius sacrae doctrinae est Dei cognitionem tradere, et non solum secundum quod in se est, sed etiam secundum quod est principium rerum et finis earum, et specialiter rationalis creaturae.</em> Aquinas, <em>ST</em> <a href="http://dhspriory.org/thomas/summa/FP/FP002.html#FPQ2OUTP1">1.2</a> div. text.</small></p>
<p><small>3. <em>Institutes of Elenctic Theology</em>, ed. James T. Dennison Jr., trans. George Musgrave Giger (Phillipsburg, NJ: P&amp;R, 1992) I.vi.i. </small></p>
<p><small>4. <em>Synopsis of a Purer Theology: Latin Text and English Translation</em>, vol. 1, Disputations 1–23, ed. Dolf te Velde, trans. Riemer A. Faber (Leiden: Brill, 2015) 6.1 (p. 151); Latin original online: <em>Synopsis purioris theologiae</em>, <a href="https://archive.org/stream/synopsispurioris00poly#page/48/mode/2up">6.1</a>.</small></p>
<p><small>5. <em>Reformed Dogmatics</em>, vol. 2, <em>God and Creation</em>, ed. John Bolt, trans. John Vriend (Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Academic, 2004), 29 (paragraph break added).</small></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>a prayer before study</title>
		<link>/journal/a-prayer-before-study/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2015 19:36:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ora et labora]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seminary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=865</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Ineffable Creator, Who out of the treasures of Thy wisdom hast appointed three hierarchies of Angels and set them in admirable order high above the heavens and hast disposed the divers portions of the universe in such marvelous array, Thou Who art called the True Source of Light and super-eminent Principle of Wisdom, be pleased to cast &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/a-prayer-before-study/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "a prayer before study"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.home.duq.edu/~bonin/thomasbibliography.html"><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-866" style="border: 1px solid black;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/ThomasAquinas-220x300.jpg" alt="Thomas Aquinas as depicted in Valle Romita Polyptych by Gentile da Fabriano" width="220" height="300" /></a>Ineffable Creator, Who out of the treasures of Thy wisdom hast appointed three hierarchies of Angels and set them in admirable order high above the heavens and hast disposed the divers portions of the universe in such marvelous array,</p>
<p>Thou Who art called the True Source of Light and super-eminent Principle of Wisdom, be pleased to cast a beam of Thy radiance upon the darkness of my mind and dispel from me the double darkness of sin and ignorance in which I have been born.</p>
<p>Thou Who makest eloquent the tongues of little children, fashion my words and pour upon my lips the grace of Thy benediction. Grant me penetration to understand, capacity to retain, method and facility in study, subtlety in interpretation and abundant grace of expression.</p>
<p>Order the beginning, direct the progress and perfect the achievement of my work,</p>
<p>Thou who art true God and Man and livest and reignest for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
<p style="text-align: right;">—Thomas Aquinas</p>
<p><span style="font-size: .8em;">Published as <em>Oratio</em> in the Raccolta #764, <em>Studiorum Ducem</em>, Encyclical of Pope Pius XI, promulgated 29 June 1923 (<a href="http://w2.vatican.va/content/pius-xi/la/encyclicals/documents/hf_p-xi_enc_19230629_studiorum-ducem.html">Latin original</a>; <a href="http://www.papalencyclicals.net/Pius11/P11STUDI.HTM">English translation</a>; cf. <a href="http://www.preces-latinae.org/thesaurus/Varia/CreatorIneff.html"><em>Oratio S. Thomae Aquinatis ante studium</em></a>.).</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Giving Thanks for Calvin Seminary’s PhD Program</title>
		<link>/journal/giving-thanks-calvin-seminarys-phd-program/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2013 22:19:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[academia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed scholasticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Muller]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seminary]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=442</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[On 9 October 2013 Calvin Seminary celebrated the twentieth year of its esteemed PhD program. The celebration’s program included Dr. James De Jong’s brief retrospective on the original vision for the PhD program and how it was established. Prof. Richard Muller delivered the plenary address, “Reflections on Two Decades of the Ph.D. Program,” after which his former &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/giving-thanks-calvin-seminarys-phd-program/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Giving Thanks for Calvin Seminary’s PhD Program"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.brill.com/products/book/church-and-school-early-modern-protestantism"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-449" title="Festschrift for Richard Muller" alt="Festschrift for Richard Muller" src="https://dash.dedeo.tk/wp-content/uploads/Muller_Festschrift.jpg" width="195" height="297" /></a></p>
<p>On 9 October 2013 Calvin Seminary <a href="http://calvinseminary.edu/2013/10/11/phd-celebration-2013/">celebrated the twentieth year</a> of its esteemed PhD program. <a href="http://calvinseminary.edu/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/PhD-Celebration-Booklet-9-2013.pdf">The celebration’s program</a> included Dr. James De Jong’s brief retrospective on the original vision for the PhD program and how it was established. Prof. Richard Muller delivered the plenary address, “Reflections on Two Decades of the Ph.D. Program,” after which his former students and colleagues presented him <a href="http://www.juniusinstitute.org/blog/muller-festschrift-presented-at-cts-phd-anniversary-celebration/">a surprise, massive festschrift</a> overflowing with no less than 55 contributions: <em><a href="http://www.brill.com/products/book/church-and-school-early-modern-protestantism">Church and School in Early Modern Protestantism: Studies in Honor of Richard A. Muller on the Maturation of a Theological Tradition</a> </em>(Leiden: Brill, 2013).</p>
<p>After <a href="http://vimeo.com/76708215">watching the presentations</a> I am even more grateful to the Lord for granting me—no doubt the least of the cadre of scholarly sojourners seeking the office of doctor with which to serve the church—a place in this program at this time in its existence and with these teachers.</p>
<div class="embed-vimeo" style="text-align: center;"><iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/76708215" width="525" height="295" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
<p>It is clear from the presentations that that the program was designed with specific ends in mind: to attract students from all over the world, to maintain a high academic standard with an emphasis on research and writing, and to specialize in Reformed catholic theology. And it is also clear that, twenty years into the program, a legacy of attaining the desired ends has been established—no doubt due to the two decades of hard work and wise leadership of the program’s leaders, Professors Feenstra and Muller, coupled with full support from the first-class faculty and library. There is much here for which God may be glorified for his abundant mercy and grace upon the program and upon its leaders.</p>
<p>The results of the program speak for themselves—literally! Her graduates are teachers, writers, professors, and institutional leaders in stations all over the globe. Even in the minute back corner of Christ’s garden in which he has planted me, the NAPARC world, the influence of CTS PhDs looms large both in numbers of teachers taking up stations in NAPARC seminaries and in the ever-growing body of top-tier publications, especially in the field of Reformed historical theology, flowing from the pens of CTS PhD’s.</p>
<p>To give a handful of cases in point (cf. <a href="http://libguides.calvin.edu/content.php?pid=16333&amp;sid=402455">the archive of downloadable CTS dissertations</a>):</p>
<ul>
<li>Jordan J. Ballor, <a href="http://www.v-r.de/en/title-2-2/covenant_causality_and_law-1008125/"><em>Covenant, Causality, and Law: A Study in the Theology of Wolfgang Musculus</em></a>, Refo500 Academic Studies (Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2012). See also Dr. Ballor’s <em><a href="http://www.getyourhandsdirtybook.com/">Get Your Hands Dirty</a></em> and editorship of the <a href="http://www.marketsandmorality.com/index.php/mandm"><em>Journal of Markets &amp; Morality</em></a>.</li>
<li>J. Mark Beach, <a href="http://www.v-r.de/en/title-2-2/christ_and_the_covenant-1002320/"><em>Christ and the Covenant: Francis Turretin’s Federal Theology as a Defense of the Doctrine of Grace</em></a>, Reformed Historical Theology 1 (Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2007). See also Dr. Beach’s editorship of the <a href="http://www.midamerica.edu/resources/journal.htm"><em>Mid-America Journal of Theology</em></a>.</li>
<li>William Ames, <a href="http://www.heritagebooks.org/a-sketch-of-the-christians-catechism-classic-reformed-theology-series/"><em>A Sketch of the Christian’s Catechism</em></a>, trans by. Todd M. Rester, Classic Reformed Theology 1 (Grand Rapids, MI: Reformation Heritage Books, 2008). See also Rester’s translation of Petrus van Mastricht, <a href="http://www.heritagebooks.org/the-best-method-of-preaching/"><em>The Best Method of Preaching</em></a> (Grand Rapids, MI: Reformation Heritage Books, 2013), a foretaste of Rester’s forthcoming multi-volume translation of Mastricht’s <em>Theoretico-practica Theologia</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p>As one who is halfway through the program and who has hit no small amount of speed bumps along the way (even some large ones such as “The Awful German Language,” as Mark Twain put it) I can testify to the program’s rigor. This is even more true following the transition from the trimester system to the semester system according to which students now write <em>three</em> twenty-five-page papers each term. But more importantly I can testify to the program’s wisdom. Though the means are painful (let me tell you, three papers per term for four terms plus course reading, assistant teaching, foreign languages, etc., was no walk in the park either for me or my family), the ends are starting to come into view.</p>
<p>I am different now than when I started the program three years ago. I care about bigger (catholic) issues. I am owning up to my own background with its limitations and prejudices. I’m learning, albeit ever so slowly, to read different languages (and hence to outgrow my monolingual, Anglophone narrowness), and I am learning to read differently (critically) in my own language. I write differently—with concrete aims and genre-appropriate methods. I teach differently—focusing on primary sources and fostering critical thinking. In these ways I see the program beginning to bear fruits in my life, and for that I give thanks to God.</p>
<p>While I stare down the still long, windy way to the PhD marathon’s finish line, it is an encouragement to be reminded along the way not only that the sowing in tears is designed to yield harvests of joy in due time but also that over the past two decades the Lord God has manifestly blessed this program with exceptional teachers whose living epistles are blessing Christ’s bride all over the world.</p>
<p><a href="http://calvinseminary.edu/2013/10/11/phd-celebration-2013/"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-443" alt="CTS PhD Celebration 2013" src="https://dash.dedeo.tk/wp-content/uploads/CTS_phd_celebration.png" width="700" height="223" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>regula sophia</title>
		<link>/journal/regula-sophia/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 09:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[academia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seminary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wisdom]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=87</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Pondering how different my academic life would be were I first to believe without wavering and then to regulate strictly my pursuit of wisdom according to James&#8217;s rule in James 3:13-18.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pondering how different my academic life would be were I first to believe without wavering and then to regulate strictly my pursuit of wisdom according to James&#8217;s rule in <a href="http://www.esvbible.org/James+3%3A13-18/">James 3:13-18</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Starting Afresh</title>
		<link>/journal/starting-afresh/</link>
		<comments>/journal/starting-afresh/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 07:10:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christianity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seminary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wisdom]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=31</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[For me this year has ushered in a season of change: new job, new city, new house, new puppies (yes, that&#8217;s a plural—thanks to G-pa O!—with all of the double-trouble craziness entailed [literally!] therein). The new job brought with it an unexpected need for a new dynamic cloud-based web server (long story, and yes, those of &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/starting-afresh/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Starting Afresh"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For me this year has ushered in a season of change: new job, new city, new house, new puppies (yes, that&#8217;s a <em>plural</em>—thanks to G-pa O!—with all of the double-trouble craziness entailed [literally!] therein). The new job brought with it an unexpected need for a new dynamic cloud-based web server (long story, and yes, those of us who were teens during the rise of 5MB AOL homepages are all insufferable webmaster-geeks deep down). Hence the time is right to bid adieu to my trusty but dated adware-supported blog of the past several years—<a title="Visit my old blog" href="http://inthylight.wordpress.com/">In Thy Light</a>—and to start afresh on “my own” ad-free corner of the cloud. Hence <em>de Deo</em>.</p>
<p>The new name (which derives from the heart of classical dogmatics: the <em>locus de Deo</em>) signals an admittedly counter-cultural note: until we humbly submit our hearts and minds to the very being which our naturalistic, materialistic, atheistic, nihilistic, idealist, restless age tells us is impossible, unreal, unnecessary, irrational, idiotic, and prudish, our hearts will remain in restless bondage to loves lesser than Love itself, and our minds will shackled to truths lesser than Truth itself.</p>
<p>It is my growing conviction that classical Christian wisdom as found in the Reformed catholic tradition offers much light for contemporary reflection upon philosophical and theological issues. Thus in accord with <a href="http://www.esvbible.org/Psalm+36%3A9/">Psalm 36:9</a> I aim to inculcate in myself and in my readers a catholic sensibility: a deep appreciation for the great, universally-acclaimed Christian teachers of the past, not merely to parrot them but to follow in their footsteps as free and skillful apprentices in Wisdom’s court who ponder all things in light of their first and final cause and thereby find true rest for heart and mind in God.</p>
<p>The simpler, sleeker, and responsive look facilitates ongoing reflection with a new audience and all of their new web-savvy devices: my students, both past and present. For the topics I teach I will endeavor to keep you updated on what I&#8217;m reading, reflections on relevant current events, and the like.</p>
<p>Though the web, perhaps more than other mediums, lends itself to pandering to imprudence (<a href="http://www.esvbible.org/Proverbs+10%3A19/">Prov. 10:19</a>), my prayer is that, by grace, my journal will be a boon to prudent reflection upon God in all things and all things in God.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/journal/starting-afresh/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
