<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Christian-Muslim relations &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/christian-muslim-relations/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 03:06:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Père Etienne Renaud</title>
		<link>/journal/pere-etienne-renaud/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2013 14:58:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian-Muslim relations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith dialog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[missiology]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=327</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Daniel Martin Varisco’s moving, three-part memoriam (1, 2, 3) for his recently deceased friend, Père Etienne Renaud, includes Renaud’s pastoral letter concerning Christian-Muslim dialog. Born out of his experience as a Christian missionary to Muslims in West Africa, this letter is worthy of pondering insofar as it is full of the expensive sort of wisdom won by lifelong commitment &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/pere-etienne-renaud/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Père Etienne Renaud"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://peres-blancs.cef.fr/etienne_renaud.htm"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-328" alt="Etienne Renaud" src="https://dash.dedeo.tk/wp-content/uploads/etienne_renaud.jpg" width="200" height="286" /></a>Daniel Martin Varisco’s moving, three-part memoriam (<a href="http://tabsir.net/?p=2220">1</a>, <a href="http://tabsir.net/?p=2221">2</a>, <a href="http://tabsir.net/?p=2222">3</a>) for his recently deceased friend, Père Etienne Renaud, includes Renaud’s <a href="http://tabsir.net/?p=2221">pastoral letter concerning Christian-Muslim dialog</a>. Born out of his experience as a Christian missionary to Muslims in West Africa, this letter is worthy of pondering insofar as it is full of the expensive sort of wisdom won by lifelong commitment to deep, loving, and real engagement with Muslims.</p>
<p>Consider Renaud’s take on Christian-Muslim dialog:</p>
<blockquote><p>True dialogue, the one in which you are wholly committed with all that you “are” can but be witness, and hence mission. The important thing is to promote with every man a true encounter, which will be both dialogue and mission at the same time. A Tunisian Professor, Mohammed Talbi, speaks of a mutual “duty of apostolate.” Since the truth of the encounter implies that at the end, each one should be able to state his inmost convictions with complete frankness. It is an ideal rarely achieved, rarely possible even, but towards which we must always tend, and which proceeds through absolute respect for one’s interlocutor.</p></blockquote>
<p>His comment on avoiding the easy temptation to abstract “Islam” from concrete relationships with Muslims is as insightful as it is apropos, perhaps especially so among Western Christians:</p>
<blockquote><p>It is essential to remind ourselves that Islam does not have only one single face and we need to guard against making global judgments, a sign that we have few contacts with people in the concrete things of their life.</p></blockquote>
<p>Finally, his encouragement to walk the gospel’s “knife edge” fosters a healthy, realistic missiological perspective on Islam over against idealistic dreams or skeptical rants:</p>
<blockquote><p>In this we must not be naïve or nurse any illusions, underestimating the difficulties of the encounter. I believe on the contrary that we need to look them straight in the face and that irenicism does not pay. But on the other hand, let us take care not to sink into scepticism and cynicism. The Gospel invites us to remain on a knife-edge: “Wise as serpents and innocent as doves.” To be both realistic and evangelical at the same time: two words which apparently are opposed to one another, but isn’t the Gospel a realism of a higher order, the only one which lasts from the viewpoint of eternity?</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pope Francis’s Message to Muslims</title>
		<link>/journal/pope-franciss-message-to-muslims/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2013 12:10:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian-Muslim relations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=260</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Pope Francis’s brief message to Muslims in celebration of Eid al-Fitr is worth a read. Politically speaking, it is interesting to note the Pope’s likely intentionally distancing himself from the perceived foibles of his predecessor’s attempts at interacting with Muslims. (Cf. “Pope Sends Message of Respect for Muslims,” New York Times, 2 August 2013.) And perhaps he &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/pope-franciss-message-to-muslims/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Pope Francis’s Message to Muslims"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-263" alt="Pope Francis" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/PopeFrancis.jpg" width="200" height="249" /></p>
<p><a href="http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/francesco/messages/pont-messages/2013/documents/papa-francesco_20130710_musulmani-ramadan_en.html">Pope Francis’s brief message to Muslims</a> in celebration of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eid_al-Fitr">Eid al-Fitr</a> is worth a read.</p>
<p>Politically speaking, it is interesting to note the Pope’s likely intentionally distancing himself from the perceived foibles of his predecessor’s attempts at interacting with Muslims. (Cf. “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/08/03/world/europe/pope-sends-message-of-respect-for-muslims.html?_r=0">Pope Sends Message of Respect for Muslims</a>,” New York Times, 2 August 2013.) And perhaps he is taking a page out of President Obama’s playbook in getting out of the gate early with positive overtures to Muslim leaders.</p>
<p>Religously speaking, we Protestants who care about Christian-Muslim relations would do well to consider the virtue themes underlying the Pope’s message of mutual respect regarding education. One passage in particular is worthy of honest reflection especially for those of us who have been influenced by the neo-Calvinist tradition with its penchant for calling down fires of antithesis not only upon adherents of others religions but also upon fellow Christians who do not agree with us on secondary and tertiary matters of faith and/or practice and who have no small amount of making up to do in the love thy neighbor as thyself department:</p>
<blockquote><p>It is clear that, when we show respect for the religion of our neighbours or when we offer them our good wishes on the occasion of a religious celebration, we simply seek to share their joy, without making reference to the content of their religious convictions.</p></blockquote>
<p>There is an important distinction at play here: the ability of a believer of religion A to share in the joy of a religious celebration for believer of religion B without believer A condoning the religious convictions of believer B or, by implication, forfeiting the truth claims of religion A in order to share in the joyous event sponsored by religion B. In other words, for a Christian, loving one’s Muslim neighbor as one’s self does not entail the removal of all religious distinctions, but it does entail a mutual commitment to basic human virtues such as respect for the other, specifically his person and his religion. Hence the Pope’s Eid well wishes do not mean that he is mixing the Meccan religion with the Roman.</p>
<p>Certainly one distinction does not world peace make. Nevertheless, for Christians courageous enough to pursue the path of social-ethical virtue <em>with</em> the other, Pope Francis’s distinction provides an important roadsign on the path of peace. Not only the streets of Egypt and Iraq but also the streets of my fair city—sunny Orlando—need such virtue now more than ever.</p>
<p>It is always easier to thank God that I am not like the other than to love the other as myself. Christians, more than any other people, ought to be the first to choose the higher way, the way of love that patiently bears with the other.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
