<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>psychology &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/psychology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 03:06:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Manton’s Christian wisdom approach to James 1:15</title>
		<link>/journal/mantons-christian-wisdom-approach-to-james-115/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2013 15:27:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Aristotle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wisdom]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=56</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When is the last time that your pastor explained the way your soul works, say, in those frequent moments when you choose to sin rather than to obey? “Umm, why would I ask my pastor a philosophical question?” might be your first reaction; for, we Protestants have a penchant for separating faith and reason. Sola &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/mantons-christian-wisdom-approach-to-james-115/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Manton’s Christian wisdom approach to James 1:15"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When is the last time that your pastor explained the way your soul works, say, in those frequent moments when you choose to sin rather than to obey? “Umm, why would I ask my pastor a philosophical question?” might be your first reaction; for, we Protestants have a penchant for separating faith and reason. <em>Sola Scriptura</em>, and all that, right? However, we used to think more colorfully and carefully: we used to think things like, “Dude, my pastor should know the way that souls work for the same reason that doctors should know the way bodies work and lawyers the way the law works—dah!”</p>
<p>Consider <a title="View Thomas Manton at the Post-Reformation Digital Library" href="http://prdl.org/author_view.php?a_id=405">Thomas Manton’s</a> (1620–1677) <a href="http://archive.org/stream/practi00mant#page/n133/mode/2up">exposition of James 1:15</a>. Herein we find a Protestant teacher—a Westminster divine, no less—using (gasp!) reason in the form of Aristotelian faculty psychology to explain the operations of the human soul in general in order that he might explain more clearly the meaning and uses (or “applications”) of James’s doctrine. “To open the process or successive inclination of the soul to sin,” he writes, “it will not be amiss to give the whole traverse of any practical matter in the soul” (p. 114). In other words, Manton suggests that Christians who know how the practical intellect works are better equipped to wield the shield of faith against Satan’s fiery darts of temptation than those who don’t (pp. 115–16).</p>
<p>Whether you think Aristotle’s psychology is sound or sophistic, the method on display here—and the metaphysic it presupposes—regarding the relation of reason and faith, philosophy and theology, is something that I think is worthy of emulation by all who call themselves Christian. For if there is truly one God who is Truth and indeed the fount of all created truths, then those truths which can be known by reason not only cannot contradict those truths which are revealed in Holy Scripture but also can and should be a ready and skilled assistant in theology’s pursuit of supreme wisdom. Inversely, the truths revealed in Holy Scripture cannot destroy or replace the truths of reason but are to purify and perfect them. Hence Manton’s willingness to put faculty psychology on the table in a discourse on James 1:15.</p>
<p>Counterintuitive as it might seem to our Protestant sensibilities, the wisdom that philosophy provides—when not despised but cherished as a gift from the God of all truth, and when applied appropriately—ought to be a boon to powerful preaching, teaching, and the building up of the saints in the gospel of Christ Jesus.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
