<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>evangelism &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/evangelism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 23:01:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Fatiha Kaouès on Evangelical Missions in the Muslim World</title>
		<link>/journal/fatiha-kaoues-on-evangelical-missions-in-the-muslim-world/</link>
		<comments>/journal/fatiha-kaoues-on-evangelical-missions-in-the-muslim-world/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 18:01:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evangelism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[missiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[missions]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=162</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Religioscope’s interview with Fatiha Kaouès is worth reading for a local, historical perspective on Evangelical missions in Egypt and Lebanon, a story in which British imperialism, American missiology, and Arab nationalism play a large role. For instance, her remark about the house church model being the most predominant current form of Protestant evangelism is interesting to &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/fatiha-kaoues-on-evangelical-missions-in-the-muslim-world/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Fatiha Kaouès on Evangelical Missions in the Muslim World"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://goo.gl/oEvPb"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-163" alt="Religioscope Interview" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/Religioscope_interview.jpg" width="200" height="274" /></a><a href="http://goo.gl/oEvPb"><em>Religioscope’s</em> interview with Fatiha Kaouès</a> is worth reading for a local, historical perspective on Evangelical missions in Egypt and Lebanon, a story in which British imperialism, American missiology, and Arab nationalism play a large role.</p>
<p>For instance, her remark about the house church model being the most predominant current form of Protestant evangelism is interesting to reflect upon in my American Presbyterian context given that:</p>
<ul>
<li>the house church movement is largely dismissed in Reformed ecclesiology,</li>
<li>and Reformed leaders don’t seem to have vibrant strategies for Muslim evangelism in the American context.</li>
</ul>
<p>From what I could gather in preparations for my class last fall, not many Reformed churches have Muslim outreaches of any kind. And when I asked Reformed pastors and leaders about how to reach Muslims in America with the gospel, the basic answer I received all around was, “one-on-one relationships.” Does this mean, then, that older strategies such as the “meetings for better understanding” approach or public debates (to bring up the elenctic side of things) are dead or passé? Is this answer truly the best contemporary wisdom, or is it a resignation that we American Evangelicals aren’t doing much of <em>anything </em>to open our hearts to our American Muslim neighbors? I’m not yet sure.</p>
<p>Further, that these Egyptian house churches have discipleship programs for MBBs brings up a topic that deserves further attention in Reformed churches: discipleship (or “catechism,” to use the older word) specifically geared toward MBBs is, from what I have gathered thus far, virtually non-existent in Reformed churches. Yet, in my view, Reformed churches have a rich, catholic theological heritage that could be a great boon to MBB catechumens (and catechists!) on topics such as Nicene trinitarianism, Chalcedonian Christology, the divine decrees, human free will, and covenant theology, all of which have parallels/touch points/reinterpretations in Islamic theology. Will the Lord raise up harvesters in this field?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/journal/fatiha-kaoues-on-evangelical-missions-in-the-muslim-world/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
