<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>phd &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/phd/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 23:01:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The five stages of CTS PhD comprehensives (part 1)</title>
		<link>/journal/the-five-stages-of-cts-phd-comprehensives-part-1/</link>
		<comments>/journal/the-five-stages-of-cts-phd-comprehensives-part-1/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2015 02:14:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[phd]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seminary]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1287</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Round 1: before the handwritten exams Denial: “I have plenty of time. I will enjoy this year. . . .” [spoken to self gleefully] Anger: “whaaaat!” upon receiving the 26-page reading list Bargaining: “Wait, maybe I still got this: I’ll use my expertly-honed skimming skills—one, two, skip a few” (after actually perusing said list a month or three later) Depression: the conflicted “oh snap, &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/the-five-stages-of-cts-phd-comprehensives-part-1/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "The five stages of CTS PhD comprehensives (part 1)"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Round 1: before the handwritten exams</h3>
<ol>
<li>Denial: “I have <em>plenty</em> of time. I will enjoy this year. . . .” [spoken to self gleefully]</li>
<li>Anger: “whaaaat!” upon receiving the <em>26-page</em> reading list</li>
<li>Bargaining: “Wait, maybe I still got this: I’ll use my expertly-honed skimming skills—one, two, skip a few” (after actually perusing said list a month or three later)</li>
<li>Depression: the conflicted “oh snap, I don’t got this” that spontaneously occurs after realizing how long it took to read the first item in first section of said list and how hard it is to skim any work entitled <em>Summa</em> or any book authored by a Puritan or Karl Barth.</li>
<li>Acceptance: revives motto from the previous two years of coursework: “I’ll sleep <em>after</em> my PhD. . . .”</li>
</ol>
<p>[9 months of zombie life intervene, the kind that is not in any way induced from binge watching The Walking Dead]</p>
<h3>Round 2: at the handwritten exams</h3>
<ol>
<li>Denial: “Five hours to write is <em>plenty</em> of time. I know everything; I got this. . . .”</li>
<li>Anger: ordinarily there is a fourfold actuality: first, upon realizing that the quantity and scope of the questions seems more fitting for a being hailing from the supernatural rather than the natural order; second, upon realizing that the “one, two, skip a few” method for parsing the reading list referenced above has resulted in a possible apophatic downside of the non-mysterious, non-worship-inducing variety; third, realizing that the first question just took 1.75 hrs to answer and that there are five more to go (tic tock); fourth, realizing how much one’s writing hand hurts since one has not handwritten anything longer than a thank you note in over a decade.</li>
<li>Bargaining: “I’ll skip that one for now, and it will look easier when I come back to it later. . . .”</li>
<li>Depression: the effect of said bargaining, the potency of which is proportionate to the now-setting-in realization that there are four more of these delightful five-hour sessions after this one.</li>
<li>Acceptance: “I’ll get to do this to <em>my</em> students some day. It will be worth it. Mwah hah hah.”</li>
</ol>
<p>[furious, spirited, truly inspired writing intervenes through very the last minute of the five-hour session; repeated fivefold]</p>
<h3>Round 3: typing up the handwritten exams</h3>
<ol>
<li>Denial: “Twenty-four hours to submit is <em>plenty</em> of time, and my answers are probably better than I first thought. I love bluebook exams in the digital age: they’re ancient-future hip and all that jazz. . . .”</li>
<li>Anger: ordinarily there is a fourfold actuality: first, upon realizing that one has just woken up after sleeping for nearly 23 hours straight and concomitantly realizing with great surprise that even zombies need a bi-annual sleep; second, upon realizing that neither the quality of one’s handwriting nor the quality of one’s answers have improved after sleeping on it; third, realizing as you’re reading how much you forgot to say in that answer, and that one, and . . . ; fourth, the five, or five-hundred “wait, <em>what</em>? I wrote <em>that</em>?” moments.</li>
<li>Bargaining: “If I choose a professional serif font and make the formatting extra nice, my answers will appear better.” [Enters typesetting hero mode. Perfect Chicago Manual of Style achieved.]</li>
<li>Depression: realizes that an improvement in the order of aesthetics does not entail an improvement in the order of cognition.</li>
<li>Acceptance: “I’ll feel better if I roll like Pilate in John 19:22. . . .” Attachment sent. [Metaphorically washes hands.]</li>
</ol>
<p>[after the fifth iteration of round three, momentary emerges from zombie cave and attempts to resume normal human functioning: remembers that he’s married; realises that his children are nine-months-worth larger-sized than he last saw them (i.e., before encountering “the list”); realizes that he might not remain married if he forgets anniversary one more time or attempts any further exams (postdoc? <em>non esse</em>—that’s not even <em>esse in potentia</em>—as far as wife is concerned); sleeps slightly more frequently than bi-annually]</p>
<p>To be continued. . . .</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/journal/the-five-stages-of-cts-phd-comprehensives-part-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
