<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" >

<channel>
	<title>Protestantism &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/protestantism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Aug 2018 18:23:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9.8</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Michael West Oborne on the Future of Philosophy and Theology</title>
		<link>/journal/michael-west-oborne-on-the-future-of-philosophy-and-theology/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2014 13:46:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Protestantism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=553</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dr. Michael West Oborne’s recent graduation address at the Dominican School of Philosophy &#38; Theology, “Philosophy and Theology’s Role in Meeting Tomorrow’s Public Policy Challenges” (Vimeo), is worth pondering in its own right. Additionally, for us Protestants who are engaged in conversation on the future of Protestantism, Oborne’s pursuit of “strategic foresight” into how the global socio-political landscape will &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/michael-west-oborne-on-the-future-of-philosophy-and-theology/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Michael West Oborne on the Future of Philosophy and Theology"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.dspt.edu/Page/574"><img class="alignright wp-image-557 size-full" style="border: 1px solid black;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/MichaelOborne.jpg" alt="Dr. Michael West Oborne" width="194" height="259" /></a><a title="Read Dr. Oborne’s bio at the Dominican School of Philosophy and Theology" href="http://www.dspt.edu/Page/574">Dr. Michael West Oborne’s</a> recent graduation address at the Dominican School of Philosophy &amp; Theology, “<a title="The video and transcript of Dr. Oborne’s address are available at the Dominican School of Philosophy and Theology" href="http://www.dspt.edu/Page/575">Philosophy and Theology’s Role in Meeting Tomorrow’s Public Policy Challenges</a>” (<a title="Watch the address at Vimeo." href="http://vimeo.com/98412573">Vimeo</a>), is worth pondering in its own right.</p>
<p>Additionally, for us Protestants who are engaged in conversation on <a href="http://www.davenanttrust.org/projects/the-future-of-protestantism/">the future of Protestantism</a>, Oborne’s pursuit of “strategic foresight” into how the global socio-political landscape will be changing over the coming decades opens a powerful and perhaps underappreciated perspective vista in Protestant dialog. Like it or not the world is changing significantly and undeniably in the areas Oborne highlights:</p>
<blockquote><p>demographics, climate change adaptation, increased integration and sophistication of technologies, the balance between public and private economic markets, resource availability and management, sustainable economic growth, equity and wealth distribution, the future of meaningful jobs and employment, geopolitical transformations, and the rule of law in societies.</p></blockquote>
<p>To take just one example:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #000000;">According to current projections, the global population will reach eight billion by 2030, and will likely reach around nine billion by 2050. In other words, the global population is projected to grow nearly 30% in the next forty years.</span></p></blockquote>
<p>According to Oborne, the socio-political effects of such growth, together with globalization, disruptive technological and biological developments and all the rest, will be drastic everywhere and will require deep rooting in philosophical and theological fundamentals in order to navigate the universal constant that will animate and dominate tomorrow’s public discourse: <em>change</em>.</p>
<p>Whether Protestants are, first, aware of such shifts and, second, producing men and women capable of navigating these tumultuous seas with a moral compass oriented toward their source and “chief and highest end” (WLC 1) are questions that need to be added to Protestant conversations on its future.</p>
<p>Further, to press deeper here and inquire a bit into the foundations of Protestant discourse, is there something valuable to be appropriated in the manner by which the Dominican tradition poses the question of tomorrow: theology <em>and philosophy’s</em> role? Is it the case that we Protestants know a thing or two about “political theology” but could learn a thing or two about political <em>philosophy </em>and another thing or two about the interrelation of faith and reason, especially in relation to social ethics and the common good?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
