<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Thomism &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/thomism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 15:39:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Olgiati on the synthetic whole</title>
		<link>/journal/olgiati-on-the-synthetic-whole/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 15:04:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Herman Bavinck]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed dogmatics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1333</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Pondering Bavinck’s outline of his Dogmatiek brought to mind a passage in the introduction to Francesco Olgiati’s The Key to the Study of St. Thomas:1 In the greater part of these recent works on St. Thomas Auinas one notes a preference for the analytic method. To be sure, this method had its merits. It was &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/olgiati-on-the-synthetic-whole/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Olgiati on the synthetic whole"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure id="attachment_1335" style="max-width: 177px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="http://it.cathopedia.org/wiki/Francesco_Olgiati" rel="attachment wp-att-1335"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Olgiati-e1455746472172.jpg" alt="Francesco Olgiati (1886–1962) " width="177" height="238" class="size-full wp-image-1335" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Francesco Olgiati<br />(1886–1962)</figcaption></figure>Pondering <a href="/bavincks-outline-of-the-reformed-dogmatics/">Bavinck’s outline</a> of his <em>Dogmatiek</em> brought to mind a passage in the introduction to Francesco Olgiati’s <em>The Key to the Study of St. Thomas</em>:<sup id="fnref-1333-1"><a href="#fn-1333-1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>
<blockquote><p>
  In the greater part of these recent works on St. Thomas Auinas one notes a preference for the analytic method. To be sure, this method had its merits. It was necessary to call attention to the theses, the theories, the several parts of the system, just as when seeking to make a person known, we begin by describing his life with its most noteworthy facts and salient exploits, as well as its most minute episodes and many seemingly negligible details. Every point of the Thomistic conception is scrutinized, illumined, discussed. After the manner of hardy explorers, the students of St. Thomas, in their loving solicitude to trace its lines with due precision, have not overlooked a single outskirt of this hallowed ground.
</p></blockquote>
<p>Olgiati then proceeds to describe the synthetic method of which his trenchant <em>Key</em> elucidates as a case in point:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  Hitherto, however, the synthetic method has not received the attention it deserves. It would seem that after the painstaking and valuable researches along the way of analysis, not enough stress has been laid on pointing out to the men of our age the wonderful unity of the whole system. Frequently, even in otherwise eminent and learned works, the manifold doctrines engross the reader’s attention without making him feel the beauty and vibration of the one and only spirit that breathes life into the whole. So it happens that many, especially among its opponents, imagine they have understood Thomism, [all] the while as a matter of fact the <em>soul</em> of St. Thomas eludes their grasp. (pp. iv–v)
</p></blockquote>
<p>The power of the sapiential approach is not in its manifold distinctions but in its striving toward synthesis; to the analytic “he who distinguishes well learns well” must be added the synthetic “distinguish to unite” if one is to penetrate “the wonderful unity of the whole system.”</p>
<p>Why? The metaphysician moves from the appearances of things to their essences, from <em>ens</em> to <em>ratio entis</em>, from participated beings to First Being, from effects to First (and Final) Cause.<sup id="fnref-1333-2"><a href="#fn-1333-2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> The theologian moves from the <em>logoi</em> of Holy Scripture to the <em>Logos</em>, from revelation deposited to revelation cogitated, from tenets of faith scattered to a body of divinity. Both perform unitive cognitive acts, referring all things to their chief and highest ends. Rarely is one person gifted with the extraordinary grace, genius, and wisdom required to perform both unitive acts in a preeminent degree. Such is the case with the <em>doctor communis</em>.</p>
<p>And such is the case too in its own way with the neo-Calvinist lights such as Kuyper and Bavinck and their intellectual forebearers, the Reformed orthodox doctors, as is slowly being recognized in contemporary Reformed Protestantism. To speculate for a minute in this digression, if someone ventured a similar synthetic study either of Bavinck’s <em>Dogmatiek</em> in particular or of Reformed dogmatics in general, I wonder whether the answer to “What is the Key?” would be similar to Olgiati’s answer with respect to Thomas.</p>
<p>Whatever the case, it seems desirable that we scholars in the field of systematic theology would every now and then take leave of the unending stream of analytic studies and pose to ourselves the synthetic questions lest we be found mistaking parts of the body for the soul, or, what might be worse, forgetting that there is a soul in our field to be found.</p>
<p>Along this line the outline of Bavinck&#8217;s <em>Dogmatics</em> provides a small opportunity to apply a synthetic <em>formalgegenstand</em> and to taste the “wonderful unity.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn-1333-1">
Trans. John S. Zybura, 2nd ed. (St. Louis: Herder, 1929).&#160;<a href="#fnref-1333-1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-1333-2">
On the unity of first and final cause, see 1. Duane H. Berquist, “<a href="http://www.aristotle-aquinas.org/peripatetikos-8/">The Truth of Aristotle’s Theology</a>,” <em>Peripatetikos</em> 8 (2011): 45–69.&#160;<a href="#fnref-1333-2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Steinmetz: “What Luther Got Wrong” about Aquinas</title>
		<link>/journal/steinmetz-what-luther-got-wrong-about-aquinas/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 23:02:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Martin Luther]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Protestant scholasticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1277</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It would be too much to assume that Aquinas will ever be as central a theologian for Protestants as he has been for Catholics. But Protestants have begun to put an end to their own self-imposed impoverishment. They have opened the ranks of the theologians with whom they are in regular conversation to include Aquinas. &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/steinmetz-what-luther-got-wrong-about-aquinas/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Steinmetz: “What Luther Got Wrong” about Aquinas"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><a href="http://divinity.duke.edu/academics/faculty/david-steinmetz"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-1278" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/DavidSteinmetz.jpg" alt="DavidSteinmetz" width="90" height="120" /></a>It would be too much to assume that Aquinas will ever be as central a theologian for Protestants as he has been for Catholics. But Protestants have begun to put an end to their own self-imposed impoverishment. They have opened the ranks of the theologians with whom they are in regular conversation to include Aquinas. It is a development long overdue.</p></blockquote>
<p>—Professor Emeritus David C. Steinmetz, “<a href="http://www.religion-online.org/showarticle.asp?title=3267">What Luther Got Wrong</a>” (repr. from <em>Christian Century</em>, August 23, 2005, pp. 23, 25)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Richard Muller lecturing this Friday: “Calvinist Thomism Revisited: William Ames (1576–1633) and the Divine Ideas”</title>
		<link>/journal/richard-muller-lecturing-this-friday-calvinist-thomism-revisited-william-ames-1576-1633-and-the-divine-ideas/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 15:47:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed scholasticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1271</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When: Friday, November 13, 3:30 p.m. EST Speaker: Professor Emeritus Richard A. Muller Topic: “Calvinist Thomism Revisited: William Ames (1576–1633) and the Divine Ideas” Location: Room 118a, Puritan Reformed Theological Seminary, Grand Rapids, MI Live stream: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6PVCdOEtS6Y Via the Junius Institute.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>When:</strong> Friday, November 13, 3:30 p.m. EST<br />
<strong>Speaker:</strong> Professor Emeritus <a href="https://calvinseminary.academia.edu/RichardMuller">Richard A. Muller</a><br />
<strong>Topic:</strong> “Calvinist Thomism Revisited: William Ames (1576–1633) and the Divine Ideas”<br />
<strong>Location:</strong> Room 118a, <a href="http://prts.edu/">Puritan Reformed Theological Seminary</a>, Grand Rapids, MI<br />
<strong>Live stream:</strong> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6PVCdOEtS6Y" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6PVCdOEtS6Y</a></p>
<p>Via the <a href="http://www.juniusinstitute.org/blog/junius-institute-colloquium-schedule-for-fall-2015/" target="_blank">Junius Institute</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>non sola ratione</title>
		<link>/journal/non-sola-ratione/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 19:41:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1220</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[If the only way open to us for the knowledge of God were solely that of the reason, the human race would remain in the blackest shadows of ignorance. —Aquinas, Cont. Gent. 1.4.4]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><a href="http://dhspriory.org/thomas/english/ContraGentiles1.htm#4"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Aquinas_Gentile_da_Fabriano1-150x150.jpg" alt="Aquinas_Gentile_da_Fabriano" width="150" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-1193" style="border: 1px solid black;"/></a>If the only way open to us for the knowledge of God were solely that of the reason, the human race would remain in the blackest shadows of ignorance.</p></blockquote>
<p style="font-size:.8em;">—Aquinas, <em><a href="http://dhspriory.org/thomas/english/ContraGentiles1.htm#4">Cont. Gent.</em> 1.4.4</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Remembering Ralph McInerny</title>
		<link>/journal/remembering-ralph-mcinerny/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2015 16:52:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophia perennis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[realism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=1004</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[“Dennis McInerny reflects on his brother’s intellectual legacy and other contemporary topics.” The realism vs. idealism  and entertainment vs. recreation bits are fresh and frank.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>“<a href="http://www.ncregister.com/daily-news/remembering-ralph-mcinerny">Dennis McInerny reflects on his brother’s intellectual legacy and other contemporary topics</a>.”</p>
<p>The realism vs. idealism  and entertainment vs. recreation bits are fresh and frank.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
