<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Wisdom &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/wisdom/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 23:01:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Do Reformed catholic theologians need philosophy?</title>
		<link>/journal/reformed-catholic-theologians-need-philosophy/</link>
		<comments>/journal/reformed-catholic-theologians-need-philosophy/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 18:05:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wisdom]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=669</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Professor Linda Zagzebski answers the question, “Do Catholic theologians need philosophy?” Her answers apply with equal force to whether Reformed catholic theologians need philosophy. For to the degree that Reformed theologizing is insular, intramural, and disconnected not only from catholic theological insights but also non-theological perspectives on universal human questions, it tends less to human &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/reformed-catholic-theologians-need-philosophy/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Do Reformed catholic theologians need philosophy?"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><iframe class='youtube-player' type='text/html' width='525' height='326' src='http://www.youtube.com/embed/rLlIYO1UXr0?version=3&#038;rel=1&#038;fs=1&#038;autohide=2&#038;showsearch=0&#038;showinfo=1&#038;iv_load_policy=1&#038;wmode=transparent' allowfullscreen='true' style='border:0;'></iframe></p>
<p><a href="http://www.ou.edu/ouphil/faculty/zagzebski/zagzebski.html">Professor Linda Zagzebski</a> answers the question, “Do Catholic theologians need philosophy?”</p>
<p>Her answers apply with equal force to whether Reformed catholic theologians need philosophy. For to the degree that Reformed theologizing is insular, intramural, and disconnected not only from catholic theological insights but also non-theological perspectives on universal human questions, it tends less to human flourishing and more to Corinthianizing; less to the true, good, and beautiful, and more to the uninteresting.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/journal/reformed-catholic-theologians-need-philosophy/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>regula sophia</title>
		<link>/journal/regula-sophia/</link>
		<comments>/journal/regula-sophia/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 09:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[academia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seminary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wisdom]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=87</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Pondering how different my academic life would be were I first to believe without wavering and then to regulate strictly my pursuit of wisdom according to James&#8217;s rule in James 3:13-18.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pondering how different my academic life would be were I first to believe without wavering and then to regulate strictly my pursuit of wisdom according to James&#8217;s rule in <a href="http://www.esvbible.org/James+3%3A13-18/">James 3:13-18</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/journal/regula-sophia/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Manton’s Christian wisdom approach to James 1:15</title>
		<link>/journal/mantons-christian-wisdom-approach-to-james-115/</link>
		<comments>/journal/mantons-christian-wisdom-approach-to-james-115/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2013 15:27:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Aristotle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wisdom]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=56</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When is the last time that your pastor explained the way your soul works, say, in those frequent moments when you choose to sin rather than to obey? “Umm, why would I ask my pastor a philosophical question?” might be your first reaction; for, we Protestants have a penchant for separating faith and reason. Sola &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/mantons-christian-wisdom-approach-to-james-115/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Manton’s Christian wisdom approach to James 1:15"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When is the last time that your pastor explained the way your soul works, say, in those frequent moments when you choose to sin rather than to obey? “Umm, why would I ask my pastor a philosophical question?” might be your first reaction; for, we Protestants have a penchant for separating faith and reason. <em>Sola Scriptura</em>, and all that, right? However, we used to think more colorfully and carefully: we used to think things like, “Dude, my pastor should know the way that souls work for the same reason that doctors should know the way bodies work and lawyers the way the law works—dah!”</p>
<p>Consider <a title="View Thomas Manton at the Post-Reformation Digital Library" href="http://prdl.org/author_view.php?a_id=405">Thomas Manton’s</a> (1620–1677) <a href="http://archive.org/stream/practi00mant#page/n133/mode/2up">exposition of James 1:15</a>. Herein we find a Protestant teacher—a Westminster divine, no less—using (gasp!) reason in the form of Aristotelian faculty psychology to explain the operations of the human soul in general in order that he might explain more clearly the meaning and uses (or “applications”) of James’s doctrine. “To open the process or successive inclination of the soul to sin,” he writes, “it will not be amiss to give the whole traverse of any practical matter in the soul” (p. 114). In other words, Manton suggests that Christians who know how the practical intellect works are better equipped to wield the shield of faith against Satan’s fiery darts of temptation than those who don’t (pp. 115–16).</p>
<p>Whether you think Aristotle’s psychology is sound or sophistic, the method on display here—and the metaphysic it presupposes—regarding the relation of reason and faith, philosophy and theology, is something that I think is worthy of emulation by all who call themselves Christian. For if there is truly one God who is Truth and indeed the fount of all created truths, then those truths which can be known by reason not only cannot contradict those truths which are revealed in Holy Scripture but also can and should be a ready and skilled assistant in theology’s pursuit of supreme wisdom. Inversely, the truths revealed in Holy Scripture cannot destroy or replace the truths of reason but are to purify and perfect them. Hence Manton’s willingness to put faculty psychology on the table in a discourse on James 1:15.</p>
<p>Counterintuitive as it might seem to our Protestant sensibilities, the wisdom that philosophy provides—when not despised but cherished as a gift from the God of all truth, and when applied appropriately—ought to be a boon to powerful preaching, teaching, and the building up of the saints in the gospel of Christ Jesus.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/journal/mantons-christian-wisdom-approach-to-james-115/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Starting Afresh</title>
		<link>/journal/starting-afresh/</link>
		<comments>/journal/starting-afresh/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 07:10:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christianity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seminary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wisdom]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=31</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[For me this year has ushered in a season of change: new job, new city, new house, new puppies (yes, that&#8217;s a plural—thanks to G-pa O!—with all of the double-trouble craziness entailed [literally!] therein). The new job brought with it an unexpected need for a new dynamic cloud-based web server (long story, and yes, those of &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/starting-afresh/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Starting Afresh"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For me this year has ushered in a season of change: new job, new city, new house, new puppies (yes, that&#8217;s a <em>plural</em>—thanks to G-pa O!—with all of the double-trouble craziness entailed [literally!] therein). The new job brought with it an unexpected need for a new dynamic cloud-based web server (long story, and yes, those of us who were teens during the rise of 5MB AOL homepages are all insufferable webmaster-geeks deep down). Hence the time is right to bid adieu to my trusty but dated adware-supported blog of the past several years—<a title="Visit my old blog" href="http://inthylight.wordpress.com/">In Thy Light</a>—and to start afresh on “my own” ad-free corner of the cloud. Hence <em>de Deo</em>.</p>
<p>The new name (which derives from the heart of classical dogmatics: the <em>locus de Deo</em>) signals an admittedly counter-cultural note: until we humbly submit our hearts and minds to the very being which our naturalistic, materialistic, atheistic, nihilistic, idealist, restless age tells us is impossible, unreal, unnecessary, irrational, idiotic, and prudish, our hearts will remain in restless bondage to loves lesser than Love itself, and our minds will shackled to truths lesser than Truth itself.</p>
<p>It is my growing conviction that classical Christian wisdom as found in the Reformed catholic tradition offers much light for contemporary reflection upon philosophical and theological issues. Thus in accord with <a href="http://www.esvbible.org/Psalm+36%3A9/">Psalm 36:9</a> I aim to inculcate in myself and in my readers a catholic sensibility: a deep appreciation for the great, universally-acclaimed Christian teachers of the past, not merely to parrot them but to follow in their footsteps as free and skillful apprentices in Wisdom’s court who ponder all things in light of their first and final cause and thereby find true rest for heart and mind in God.</p>
<p>The simpler, sleeker, and responsive look facilitates ongoing reflection with a new audience and all of their new web-savvy devices: my students, both past and present. For the topics I teach I will endeavor to keep you updated on what I&#8217;m reading, reflections on relevant current events, and the like.</p>
<p>Though the web, perhaps more than other mediums, lends itself to pandering to imprudence (<a href="http://www.esvbible.org/Proverbs+10%3A19/">Prov. 10:19</a>), my prayer is that, by grace, my journal will be a boon to prudent reflection upon God in all things and all things in God.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/journal/starting-afresh/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
