<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Sermons &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/category/sermons/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 15:39:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>“Do Not Quarrel on the Way”: a sermon on Genesis 45:24</title>
		<link>/journal/quarrel-way-sermon-genesis-4524/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2013 04:06:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Sermons]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[anger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Decalogue]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genesis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[murder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Westminster Larger Catechism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=420</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Recently I preached on what at first glance seems like a throw-away line in the climactic reunion scene of the Joseph story: “do not quarrel on the way.” This is the last thing that Joseph says to his brothers before he sends them back to Canaan for the second time, and it only makes sense if &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/quarrel-way-sermon-genesis-4524/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "“Do Not Quarrel on the Way”: a sermon on Genesis 45:24"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Giovanni_Andrea_de_Ferrari_-_%27Joseph%27s_Coat_Brought_to_Jacob%27,_oil_on_canvas,_c._1640,_El_Paso_Museum_of_Art.jpg"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-421" style="margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; border: 1px solid black;" title="Giovanni Andrea de Ferrari — Joseph's Coat brought to Jacob" alt="Giovanni Andrea de Ferrari — Joseph's Coat brought to Jacob" src="https://dash.dedeo.tk/wp-content/uploads/Giovanni_Andrea_de_Ferrari—Josephs_Coat.jpg" width="279" height="240" /></a></p>
<p>Recently I preached on what at first glance seems like a throw-away line in the climactic reunion scene of the Joseph story: “do not quarrel on the way.” This is the last thing that Joseph says to his brothers before he sends them back to Canaan for the <em>second</em> time, and it only makes sense if you put it in the context of the dramatic transition from murderous hatred in the opening scenes to reconciliation and brotherly love in the climax.</p>
<p>Despite its brevity and enigmatic character, I find the importance of this command—both for Joseph’s brothers and for contemporary life—to lie in its relation to the sixth commandment. Consider, for instance, how the Larger Catechism explains the duties and prohibitions of this commandment in line with Jesus’s teaching on anger in Matthew 5.</p>
<blockquote><p>Q. 134. Which is the sixth commandment?<br />
A. The sixth commandment is, Thou shalt not kill.</p>
<p>Q. 135. What are the duties required in the sixth commandment?<br />
A. The duties required in the sixth commandment are, all careful studies, and lawful endeavors, to preserve the life of ourselves and others by resisting all thoughts and purposes, subduing all passions, and avoiding all occasions, temptations, and practices, which tend to the unjust taking away the life of any; by just defense thereof against violence, patient bearing of the hand of God, quietness of mind, cheerfulness of spirit; a sober use of meat, drink, physic, sleep, labor, and recreations; by charitable thoughts, love, compassion, meekness, gentleness, kindness; peaceable, mild and courteous speeches and behavior; forbearance, readiness to be reconciled, patient bearing and forgiving of injuries, and requiting good for evil; comforting and succoring the distressed, and protecting and defending the innocent.</p>
<p>Q. 136. What are the sins forbidden in the sixth commandment?<br />
A. The sins forbidden in the sixth commandment are, all taking away the life of ourselves, or of others, except in case of public justice, lawful war, or necessary defense; the neglecting or withdrawing the lawful and necessary means of preservation of life; sinful anger, hatred, envy, desire of revenge; all excessive passions, distracting cares; immoderate use of meat, drink, labor, and recreations; provoking words, oppression, quarreling, striking, wounding, and whatsoever else tends to the destruction of the life of any.</p></blockquote>
<p>There is likely no message needed more in our quarrelsome and bloodthirsty times—both within and without the church—than demanding brotherly unity as a means of fostering human flourishing. And there is likely no moral imperative that blatantly reveals our moral failures as humans and clearly shows us our need for the Father’s love, Christ’s mediation, and the Holy Spirit’s powerful indwelling than that which Joseph commands his brothers.</p>
<audio class="wp-audio-shortcode" id="audio-420-2" preload="none" style="width: 100%;" controls="controls"><source type="audio/mpeg" src="http://ia601004.us.archive.org/12/items/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.mp3?_=2" /><a href="http://ia601004.us.archive.org/12/items/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.mp3">http://ia601004.us.archive.org/12/items/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.mp3</a></audio>
<p>(download: <a href="http://archive.org/download/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.mp3">MP3</a>; <a href="http://archive.org/download/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.ogg">OGG</a>; <a href="http://archive.org/download/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.4">FLAC</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	<enclosure url="http://ia601004.us.archive.org/12/items/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.mp3" length="57111552" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="http://archive.org/download/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.mp3" length="0" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="http://archive.org/download/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.ogg" length="0" type="audio/ogg" />
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>“I am praying for them”: a sermon on Exodus 32 and John 17:9</title>
		<link>/journal/i-am-praying-for-them/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2013 18:40:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sermons]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian life]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Larger Catechism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[prayer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Westminster Standards]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=250</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[https://archive.org/download/IAmPrayingForThem/2013.07.21%20-%20I%20am%20praying%20for%20them.mp3 That the resurrected Christ continually intercedes for all his people from the Father&#8217;s heavenly throne is a deep well of grace. In this catechetical sermon I draw&#160;living water from this wonderful well by unfolding the Larger Catechism’s teaching on Jesus’s heavenly intercession: Q. 55. How doth Christ make intercession? A. Christ maketh intercession, by &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/i-am-praying-for-them/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "“I am praying for them”: a sermon on Exodus 32 and John 17:9"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<audio class="wp-audio-shortcode" id="audio-250-4" preload="none" style="width: 100%;" controls="controls"><source type="audio/mpeg" src="https://archive.org/download/IAmPrayingForThem/2013.07.21%20-%20I%20am%20praying%20for%20them.mp3?_=4" /><a href="https://archive.org/download/IAmPrayingForThem/2013.07.21%20-%20I%20am%20praying%20for%20them.mp3">https://archive.org/download/IAmPrayingForThem/2013.07.21%20-%20I%20am%20praying%20for%20them.mp3</a></audio>
<p><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-256" alt="WaterDroplet" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/WaterDroplet.jpg" width="300" height="200" />That the resurrected Christ continually intercedes for all his people from the Father&#8217;s heavenly throne is a deep well of grace. In this catechetical sermon I draw&nbsp;living water from this wonderful well by unfolding the <a href="http://opc.org/lc.html">Larger Catechism’s</a> teaching on Jesus’s heavenly intercession:</p>
<blockquote><p>Q. 55. How doth Christ make intercession?<br />
A. Christ maketh intercession, by his appearing in our nature continually before the Father in heaven, in the merit of his obedience and sacrifice on earth, declaring his will to have it applied to all believers; answering all accusations against them, and procuring for them quiet of conscience, notwithstanding daily failings, access with boldness to the throne of grace, and acceptance of their persons and services.</p></blockquote>
<p>I use Moses’s temporary, earthly, and inglorious intercession in Exodus 32 as a backdrop for contrasting Jesus’s eternal, heavenly, and glorious intercession of which Jesus gives us a glimpse in his high priestly prayer (John 17:9).</p>
<p>(<a href="https://archive.org/download/IAmPrayingForThem/2013.07.21%20-%20I%20am%20praying%20for%20them.mp3">download MP3</a>; 5.4 MB)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
