<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Dies und Das &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/category/miscellaneous/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 15:39:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Ellebogius: “When in doubt . . .”</title>
		<link>/journal/ellebogius-when-in-doubt/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2016 20:11:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1413</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Regarding God’s goodness, all the Protestant doctors of high esteem share the same rule: if there is the slightest doubt, go Trappist; if the doubt persists, go Dubbel; if the persistence persists, go Tripel. Against such things, when conjoined with moderation and gratitude, no doubt however dark can succeed inasmuch as the good is self-diffusive. &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/ellebogius-when-in-doubt/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Ellebogius: “When in doubt . . .”"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>
  Regarding God’s goodness, all the Protestant doctors of high esteem share the same rule: if there is the slightest doubt, go <a href="http://www.trappist.be/en/pages/trappist-beers">Trappist</a>; if the doubt persists, go <a href="http://www.trappistwestmalle.be/en/page/dubbel.aspx">Dubbel</a>; if the persistence persists, go <a href="http://www.trappistwestmalle.be/en/page/tripel.aspx">Tripel</a>. Against such things, when conjoined with moderation and gratitude, no doubt however dark can succeed inasmuch as the good is self-diffusive.
</p></blockquote>
<p>— Cornelius Ellebogius</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Glossa ordinaria project</title>
		<link>/journal/glossa-ordinaria-project/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 19:07:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Biblical interpretation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[historical exegesis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1401</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[http://www.pims.ca/academics/news-and-announcements/post/the-glossed-bible-editions-and-studies-of-the-medieval-sacra-pagina Despite its popularity as a textbook, and its importance to the development of theology in the twelfth and thirteenth centuries and to medieval thought more widely, the Gloss on the Bible has never been fully edited. In order to rectify this deficiency, the series proposes carefully to edit the Latin text of each book &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/glossa-ordinaria-project/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Glossa ordinaria project"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.pims.ca/academics/news-and-announcements/post/the-glossed-bible-editions-and-studies-of-the-medieval-sacra-pagina">http://www.pims.ca/academics/news-and-announcements/post/the-glossed-bible-editions-and-studies-of-the-medieval-sacra-pagina</a></p>
<blockquote><p>
  Despite its popularity as a textbook, and its importance to the development of theology in the twelfth and thirteenth centuries and to medieval thought more widely, the Gloss on the Bible has never been fully edited.</p>
<p>  In order to rectify this deficiency, the series proposes carefully to edit the Latin text of each book (and, indeed, of each version) of the Gloss.
</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Olgiati on the synthetic whole</title>
		<link>/journal/olgiati-on-the-synthetic-whole/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 15:04:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Herman Bavinck]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed dogmatics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1333</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Pondering Bavinck’s outline of his Dogmatiek brought to mind a passage in the introduction to Francesco Olgiati’s The Key to the Study of St. Thomas:1 In the greater part of these recent works on St. Thomas Auinas one notes a preference for the analytic method. To be sure, this method had its merits. It was &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/olgiati-on-the-synthetic-whole/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Olgiati on the synthetic whole"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure id="attachment_1335" style="max-width: 177px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="http://it.cathopedia.org/wiki/Francesco_Olgiati" rel="attachment wp-att-1335"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Olgiati-e1455746472172.jpg" alt="Francesco Olgiati (1886–1962) " width="177" height="238" class="size-full wp-image-1335" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Francesco Olgiati<br />(1886–1962)</figcaption></figure>Pondering <a href="/bavincks-outline-of-the-reformed-dogmatics/">Bavinck’s outline</a> of his <em>Dogmatiek</em> brought to mind a passage in the introduction to Francesco Olgiati’s <em>The Key to the Study of St. Thomas</em>:<sup id="fnref-1333-1"><a href="#fn-1333-1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>
<blockquote><p>
  In the greater part of these recent works on St. Thomas Auinas one notes a preference for the analytic method. To be sure, this method had its merits. It was necessary to call attention to the theses, the theories, the several parts of the system, just as when seeking to make a person known, we begin by describing his life with its most noteworthy facts and salient exploits, as well as its most minute episodes and many seemingly negligible details. Every point of the Thomistic conception is scrutinized, illumined, discussed. After the manner of hardy explorers, the students of St. Thomas, in their loving solicitude to trace its lines with due precision, have not overlooked a single outskirt of this hallowed ground.
</p></blockquote>
<p>Olgiati then proceeds to describe the synthetic method of which his trenchant <em>Key</em> elucidates as a case in point:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  Hitherto, however, the synthetic method has not received the attention it deserves. It would seem that after the painstaking and valuable researches along the way of analysis, not enough stress has been laid on pointing out to the men of our age the wonderful unity of the whole system. Frequently, even in otherwise eminent and learned works, the manifold doctrines engross the reader’s attention without making him feel the beauty and vibration of the one and only spirit that breathes life into the whole. So it happens that many, especially among its opponents, imagine they have understood Thomism, [all] the while as a matter of fact the <em>soul</em> of St. Thomas eludes their grasp. (pp. iv–v)
</p></blockquote>
<p>The power of the sapiential approach is not in its manifold distinctions but in its striving toward synthesis; to the analytic “he who distinguishes well learns well” must be added the synthetic “distinguish to unite” if one is to penetrate “the wonderful unity of the whole system.”</p>
<p>Why? The metaphysician moves from the appearances of things to their essences, from <em>ens</em> to <em>ratio entis</em>, from participated beings to First Being, from effects to First (and Final) Cause.<sup id="fnref-1333-2"><a href="#fn-1333-2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> The theologian moves from the <em>logoi</em> of Holy Scripture to the <em>Logos</em>, from revelation deposited to revelation cogitated, from tenets of faith scattered to a body of divinity. Both perform unitive cognitive acts, referring all things to their chief and highest ends. Rarely is one person gifted with the extraordinary grace, genius, and wisdom required to perform both unitive acts in a preeminent degree. Such is the case with the <em>doctor communis</em>.</p>
<p>And such is the case too in its own way with the neo-Calvinist lights such as Kuyper and Bavinck and their intellectual forebearers, the Reformed orthodox doctors, as is slowly being recognized in contemporary Reformed Protestantism. To speculate for a minute in this digression, if someone ventured a similar synthetic study either of Bavinck’s <em>Dogmatiek</em> in particular or of Reformed dogmatics in general, I wonder whether the answer to “What is the Key?” would be similar to Olgiati’s answer with respect to Thomas.</p>
<p>Whatever the case, it seems desirable that we scholars in the field of systematic theology would every now and then take leave of the unending stream of analytic studies and pose to ourselves the synthetic questions lest we be found mistaking parts of the body for the soul, or, what might be worse, forgetting that there is a soul in our field to be found.</p>
<p>Along this line the outline of Bavinck&#8217;s <em>Dogmatics</em> provides a small opportunity to apply a synthetic <em>formalgegenstand</em> and to taste the “wonderful unity.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn-1333-1">
Trans. John S. Zybura, 2nd ed. (St. Louis: Herder, 1929).&#160;<a href="#fnref-1333-1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-1333-2">
On the unity of first and final cause, see 1. Duane H. Berquist, “<a href="http://www.aristotle-aquinas.org/peripatetikos-8/">The Truth of Aristotle’s Theology</a>,” <em>Peripatetikos</em> 8 (2011): 45–69.&#160;<a href="#fnref-1333-2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The five stages of CTS PhD comprehensives (part 1)</title>
		<link>/journal/the-five-stages-of-cts-phd-comprehensives-part-1/</link>
		<comments>/journal/the-five-stages-of-cts-phd-comprehensives-part-1/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2015 02:14:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[phd]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seminary]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1287</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Round 1: before the handwritten exams Denial: “I have plenty of time. I will enjoy this year. . . .” [spoken to self gleefully] Anger: “whaaaat!” upon receiving the 26-page reading list Bargaining: “Wait, maybe I still got this: I’ll use my expertly-honed skimming skills—one, two, skip a few” (after actually perusing said list a month or three later) Depression: the conflicted “oh snap, &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/the-five-stages-of-cts-phd-comprehensives-part-1/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "The five stages of CTS PhD comprehensives (part 1)"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Round 1: before the handwritten exams</h3>
<ol>
<li>Denial: “I have <em>plenty</em> of time. I will enjoy this year. . . .” [spoken to self gleefully]</li>
<li>Anger: “whaaaat!” upon receiving the <em>26-page</em> reading list</li>
<li>Bargaining: “Wait, maybe I still got this: I’ll use my expertly-honed skimming skills—one, two, skip a few” (after actually perusing said list a month or three later)</li>
<li>Depression: the conflicted “oh snap, I don’t got this” that spontaneously occurs after realizing how long it took to read the first item in first section of said list and how hard it is to skim any work entitled <em>Summa</em> or any book authored by a Puritan or Karl Barth.</li>
<li>Acceptance: revives motto from the previous two years of coursework: “I’ll sleep <em>after</em> my PhD. . . .”</li>
</ol>
<p>[9 months of zombie life intervene, the kind that is not in any way induced from binge watching The Walking Dead]</p>
<h3>Round 2: at the handwritten exams</h3>
<ol>
<li>Denial: “Five hours to write is <em>plenty</em> of time. I know everything; I got this. . . .”</li>
<li>Anger: ordinarily there is a fourfold actuality: first, upon realizing that the quantity and scope of the questions seems more fitting for a being hailing from the supernatural rather than the natural order; second, upon realizing that the “one, two, skip a few” method for parsing the reading list referenced above has resulted in a possible apophatic downside of the non-mysterious, non-worship-inducing variety; third, realizing that the first question just took 1.75 hrs to answer and that there are five more to go (tic tock); fourth, realizing how much one’s writing hand hurts since one has not handwritten anything longer than a thank you note in over a decade.</li>
<li>Bargaining: “I’ll skip that one for now, and it will look easier when I come back to it later. . . .”</li>
<li>Depression: the effect of said bargaining, the potency of which is proportionate to the now-setting-in realization that there are four more of these delightful five-hour sessions after this one.</li>
<li>Acceptance: “I’ll get to do this to <em>my</em> students some day. It will be worth it. Mwah hah hah.”</li>
</ol>
<p>[furious, spirited, truly inspired writing intervenes through very the last minute of the five-hour session; repeated fivefold]</p>
<h3>Round 3: typing up the handwritten exams</h3>
<ol>
<li>Denial: “Twenty-four hours to submit is <em>plenty</em> of time, and my answers are probably better than I first thought. I love bluebook exams in the digital age: they’re ancient-future hip and all that jazz. . . .”</li>
<li>Anger: ordinarily there is a fourfold actuality: first, upon realizing that one has just woken up after sleeping for nearly 23 hours straight and concomitantly realizing with great surprise that even zombies need a bi-annual sleep; second, upon realizing that neither the quality of one’s handwriting nor the quality of one’s answers have improved after sleeping on it; third, realizing as you’re reading how much you forgot to say in that answer, and that one, and . . . ; fourth, the five, or five-hundred “wait, <em>what</em>? I wrote <em>that</em>?” moments.</li>
<li>Bargaining: “If I choose a professional serif font and make the formatting extra nice, my answers will appear better.” [Enters typesetting hero mode. Perfect Chicago Manual of Style achieved.]</li>
<li>Depression: realizes that an improvement in the order of aesthetics does not entail an improvement in the order of cognition.</li>
<li>Acceptance: “I’ll feel better if I roll like Pilate in John 19:22. . . .” Attachment sent. [Metaphorically washes hands.]</li>
</ol>
<p>[after the fifth iteration of round three, momentary emerges from zombie cave and attempts to resume normal human functioning: remembers that he’s married; realises that his children are nine-months-worth larger-sized than he last saw them (i.e., before encountering “the list”); realizes that he might not remain married if he forgets anniversary one more time or attempts any further exams (postdoc? <em>non esse</em>—that’s not even <em>esse in potentia</em>—as far as wife is concerned); sleeps slightly more frequently than bi-annually]</p>
<p>To be continued. . . .</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/journal/the-five-stages-of-cts-phd-comprehensives-part-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Steinmetz: “What Luther Got Wrong” about Aquinas</title>
		<link>/journal/steinmetz-what-luther-got-wrong-about-aquinas/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 23:02:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Martin Luther]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Protestant scholasticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1277</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It would be too much to assume that Aquinas will ever be as central a theologian for Protestants as he has been for Catholics. But Protestants have begun to put an end to their own self-imposed impoverishment. They have opened the ranks of the theologians with whom they are in regular conversation to include Aquinas. &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/steinmetz-what-luther-got-wrong-about-aquinas/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Steinmetz: “What Luther Got Wrong” about Aquinas"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><a href="http://divinity.duke.edu/academics/faculty/david-steinmetz"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-1278" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/DavidSteinmetz.jpg" alt="DavidSteinmetz" width="90" height="120" /></a>It would be too much to assume that Aquinas will ever be as central a theologian for Protestants as he has been for Catholics. But Protestants have begun to put an end to their own self-imposed impoverishment. They have opened the ranks of the theologians with whom they are in regular conversation to include Aquinas. It is a development long overdue.</p></blockquote>
<p>—Professor Emeritus David C. Steinmetz, “<a href="http://www.religion-online.org/showarticle.asp?title=3267">What Luther Got Wrong</a>” (repr. from <em>Christian Century</em>, August 23, 2005, pp. 23, 25)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Richard Muller lecturing this Friday: “Calvinist Thomism Revisited: William Ames (1576–1633) and the Divine Ideas”</title>
		<link>/journal/richard-muller-lecturing-this-friday-calvinist-thomism-revisited-william-ames-1576-1633-and-the-divine-ideas/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 15:47:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed scholasticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1271</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When: Friday, November 13, 3:30 p.m. EST Speaker: Professor Emeritus Richard A. Muller Topic: “Calvinist Thomism Revisited: William Ames (1576–1633) and the Divine Ideas” Location: Room 118a, Puritan Reformed Theological Seminary, Grand Rapids, MI Live stream: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6PVCdOEtS6Y Via the Junius Institute.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>When:</strong> Friday, November 13, 3:30 p.m. EST<br />
<strong>Speaker:</strong> Professor Emeritus <a href="https://calvinseminary.academia.edu/RichardMuller">Richard A. Muller</a><br />
<strong>Topic:</strong> “Calvinist Thomism Revisited: William Ames (1576–1633) and the Divine Ideas”<br />
<strong>Location:</strong> Room 118a, <a href="http://prts.edu/">Puritan Reformed Theological Seminary</a>, Grand Rapids, MI<br />
<strong>Live stream:</strong> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6PVCdOEtS6Y" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6PVCdOEtS6Y</a></p>
<p>Via the <a href="http://www.juniusinstitute.org/blog/junius-institute-colloquium-schedule-for-fall-2015/" target="_blank">Junius Institute</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Thanksgiving for American Independence</title>
		<link>/journal/a-thanksgiving-for-american-independence/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2015 11:14:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[America]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[American religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Independence Day]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1110</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Almighty God, who hast made of one blood all nations of men to dwell on all the face of the earth, and hast determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of their habitation; We yield thee our unfeigned thanks and praise for the wonderful and mighty deliverance whereby thou didst raise up the people &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/a-thanksgiving-for-american-independence/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "A Thanksgiving for American Independence"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-1112" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Flag_of_the_United_States.png" alt="Flag_of_the_United_States" width="300" height="158" />Almighty God, who hast made of one blood all nations of men to dwell on all the face of the earth, and hast determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of their habitation; We yield thee our unfeigned thanks and praise for the wonderful and mighty deliverance whereby thou didst raise up the people of these States from dependence and distress to a name and a place among the nations, and give to them this good land for an inheritance. Not by our might or for our merit, but of thy goodness and through thy power and providence we are what we are this day before thee; and therefore not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy name be ascribed all honor and glory, from generation to generation; through Jesus Christ our Lord. <em>Amen</em>.</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=F2dAAQAAMAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"><em>The Book of Common Prayer as Amended by the Westminster Divines, A. D. 1661</em></a>, ed. Charles W. Shields (Philadelphia: James Claxton, 1867), 351–52.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Translations of Aquinas’s Job commentary, Sentences commentary moving along</title>
		<link>/journal/translations-of-aquinass-job-commentary-sentences-commentary-moving-along/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2015 21:54:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1098</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[http://thomistica.net/news/2015/5/14/bilingual-latinenglish-hardcover-editions-of-aquinas-update These high quality hardbacks are excellent Latin-English editions of Thomas’s works. Looking forward to the next arrivals in this prestigious publishing project.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://thomistica.net/news/2015/5/14/bilingual-latinenglish-hardcover-editions-of-aquinas-update">http://thomistica.net/news/2015/5/14/bilingual-latinenglish-hardcover-editions-of-aquinas-update</a></p>
<p>These high quality hardbacks are excellent<em> </em>Latin-English editions of Thomas’s works. Looking forward to the next arrivals in this prestigious publishing project.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Truth, style, and the secret of writing</title>
		<link>/journal/truth-style-and-the-secret-of-writing/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2015 15:44:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[writing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1078</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The qualities of style may be set out under as many headings as you will; but they can all be contained, I think, in these three words: truth, individuality, and simplicity; unless you prefer to sum it all up in a single formula; one must write truly. A style is true when it corresponds to a &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/truth-style-and-the-secret-of-writing/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Truth, style, and the secret of writing"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure id="attachment_994" style="max-width: 207px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonin_Sertillanges"><img class="size-full wp-image-994" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/Antonin-Dalmace-Sertillanges-e1431547456881.jpg" alt="Antonin Sertillanges (1863–1948)" width="207" height="263" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Antonin Sertillanges<br />(1863–1948)</figcaption></figure>
<blockquote><p>The qualities of style may be set out under as many headings as you will; but they can all be contained, I think, in these three words: truth, individuality, and simplicity; unless you prefer to sum it all up in a single formula; one must write <em>truly.</em></p>
<p>A style is true when it corresponds to a necessity of thought and when it keeps intimate contact with things.</p>
<p>[&#8230;]</p>
<p>Thinking is conceiving what is; writing truly, that is writing according to one&#8217;s thought, is revealing what is, not stringing sentences together. And so the secret of writing is to stand and study things ardently, until they speak to you and themselves determine their own expression.</p></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: 0.8em; text-align: right;">Antonin Sertillanges, <cite><a href="http://www.worldcat.org/title/intellectual-life-its-spirit-conditions-methods/oclc/6033719&amp;referer=brief_results">The Intellectual Life: Its Spirit, Conditions, Methods</a></cite> (repr. 1998; Washington DC: Catholic University of America Press, 1987), 202–04.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Read less, read better</title>
		<link>/journal/what-to-read/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2015 20:18:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[academia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophia perennis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reading]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=1017</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Read only those books in which leading ideas are expressed at first hand. These are not very numerous. Books repeat one another, water one another down, or contradict one another, and that too is a kind of repetition. On examination we find that discoveries in thought are rare. The old stock or rather the permanent &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/what-to-read/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Read less, read better"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure id="attachment_994" style="max-width: 207px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonin_Sertillanges"><img class="size-full wp-image-994" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/Antonin-Dalmace-Sertillanges-e1431547456881.jpg" alt="Antonin Sertillanges (1863–1948)" width="207" height="263" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Antonin Sertillanges<br />(1863–1948)</figcaption></figure>
<blockquote><p>Read only those books in which leading ideas are expressed at first hand. These are not very numerous. Books repeat one another, water one another down, or contradict one another, and that too is a kind of repetition. On examination we find that discoveries in thought are rare. The old stock or rather the permanent stock of ideas is the best; one must take one’s stand on it in order truly to commune with the intelligence of man, far from petty, stammering, squabbling individualities.<br />
[&#8230;]<br />
. . . love the eternal books that express eternal truths.</p></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: 0.8em; text-align: right;">Antonin Sertillanges, <cite><a href="http://www.worldcat.org/title/intellectual-life-its-spirit-conditions-methods/oclc/6033719&amp;referer=brief_results">The Intellectual Life: Its Spirit, Conditions, Methods</a></cite> (repr. 1998; Washington DC: Catholic University of America Press, 1987), 150–51.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
