<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>faith and reason &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/faith-and-reason/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 15:39:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Verum cum vero non pugnat:  Maccovius, Voetius, &#038; Bavinck on philosophy and theology</title>
		<link>/journal/verum-cum-vero-non-pugnat-maccovius-voetius-bavinck-on-philosophy-and-theology/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 14:52:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed scholasticism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=1495</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[First, a few theses from Johannes Maccovius’s Theological and Philosophical Distinctions and Rules, ch. 1, On Holy Scripture: XXXVIII. The object of theology and the object of philosophy are diverse and distinct. XXXIX. Truth never runs counter to (pugno) truth. XL. Sound reason and theology do not conflict (pugno).1 Second, a thesis from Gisbertus Voetius’s &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/verum-cum-vero-non-pugnat-maccovius-voetius-bavinck-on-philosophy-and-theology/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Verum cum vero non pugnat:  Maccovius, Voetius, &#038; Bavinck on philosophy and theology"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>First, a few theses from Johannes Maccovius’s <em>Theological and Philosophical Distinctions and Rules</em>, ch. 1, On Holy Scripture:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  XXXVIII. The object of theology and the object of philosophy are diverse and distinct.</p>
<p>  XXXIX. Truth never runs counter to (pugno) truth.</p>
<p>  XL. Sound reason and theology do not conflict (pugno).<sup id="fnref-1495-1"><a href="#fn-1495-1" class="jetpack-footnote">1</a></sup>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Second, a thesis from Gisbertus Voetius’s Thersites, self-tormentor:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  I. The light of nature does not fight with (pugno) the light of grace, nor philosophy with theology. Therefore, a-theological, and also doing injury to God and His truth, are those who condemn philosophy.<sup id="fnref-1495-2"><a href="#fn-1495-2" class="jetpack-footnote">2</a></sup>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Third, a summation from Herman Bavinck’s <em>Reformed Dogmatics</em>, which employs the “non pugno” motif in Bavinck’s European narrative style:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  If theology thus has its internal principle not in faith as such but in believing reflection, the task of reason in theological science calls for further definition. In this context we must first of all and fundamentally reject the notion that regards faith and reason as two independent powers engaging in a life-and-death struggle with each other. . . . Faith, the faith by which we believe (de fides qua creditur), is not an organ or faculty next to or above reason but a disposition or habit of reason itself. . . . Faith, therefore, does not relieve Christians of the desire to study and reflect; rather it spurs them on to the end. Nature is not destroyed by regeneration but restored.</p>
<p>  Believers who want to devote themselves to the study of theology, accordingly, must prepare their minds for the task awaiting them. There is no admission to the temple of theology except by way of the study of the arts. Indispensable to the practitioner of the science of theology is philosophical, historical, and linguistic preparatory training.<sup id="fnref-1495-3"><a href="#fn-1495-3" class="jetpack-footnote">3</a></sup>
</p></blockquote>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn-1495-1">
<a href="https://archive.org/stream/ned-kbn-all-00003652-001#page/n44/mode/2up"><em>Distinctiones et regulae theologicae ac philosophicae</em></a> (1653), 20-21; translation from <a href="http://www.tua.nl/index.php?item=artikel&amp;paginaID=19&amp;artikelID=19"><em>Scholastic Discourse: Johannes Maccovius (1588–1644) on Theological and Philosophical Distinctions and Rules</em></a>, translated and edited by Willem J. van Asselt, Michael D. Bell, Gert van den Brink, Rein Ferwerda (Apeldoorn: Instituut voor Reformatieonderzoek, 2009), 78–81.&#160;<a href="#fnref-1495-1">&#8617;</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-1495-2">
<a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=ZIljAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA347#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true"><em>Thersites heautontimorumenos</em></a> (Utrecht : Ex Officinâ Abrahami ab Herwiick &amp; Hermanni Ribbii, 1635), 347; translation from Aza Goudriaan, <a href="http://www.brill.com/reformed-orthodoxy-and-philosophy-1625-1750"><em>Reformed Orthodoxy and Philosophy, 1625–1750: Gisbertus Voetius, Petrus Van Mastricht, and Anthonius Driessen</em></a>, Brill’s Series in Church History 26 (Brill, 2006), 30; cf. B. Hoon Woo, “<a href="https://www.academia.edu/3325870/_The_Understanding_of_Gisbertus_Voetius_and_Ren%C3%A9_Descartes_on_the_Relationship_of_Faith_and_Reason_and_Theology_and_Philosophy_Westminster_Theological_Journal_75_no._1_2013_45_63">‘The Understanding of Gisbertus Voetius and René Descartes on the Relationship of Faith and Reason, and Theology and Philosophy</a>,” <em>Westminster Theological Journal</em> 75, No. 1 (2013): 45–63; quote referenced at p. 54.&#160;<a href="#fnref-1495-2">&#8617;</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-1495-3">
Vol. 1, <em>Prolegomena</em>, trans. John Vriend, ed. John Bolt (Grand Rapids: Baker Academic, 2003), 616–17; Bavinck quotes Voetius&#8217;s disputations at 616n41; see also 618n46 for Bavinck’s short list of sources on the philosophy-theology relation, which includes the same disputations by Voetius.&#160;<a href="#fnref-1495-3">&#8617;</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Aquinas: the old woman’s faith vs. the philosophers’ reason</title>
		<link>/journal/aquinas-the-old-womans-faith-vs-the-philosophers-reason/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 20:24:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=1433</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[&#8220;The just man liveth by faith.&#8221; [Habakkuk 2:4] This is evident in that no one of the philosophers before the coming of Christ could, through his own powers, know God and the means necessary for salvation as well as any old woman since Christ’s coming knows Him through faith. Thomas Aquinas, Catechical Instructions of St. &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/aquinas-the-old-womans-faith-vs-the-philosophers-reason/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Aquinas: the old woman’s faith vs. the philosophers’ reason"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>
  &#8220;The just man liveth by faith.&#8221; [Habakkuk 2:4] This is evident in that no one of the philosophers before the coming of Christ could, through his own powers, know God and the means necessary for salvation as well as any old woman since Christ’s coming knows Him through faith.
</p></blockquote>
<p>Thomas Aquinas, <em>Catechical Instructions of St. Thomas Aquinas</em>, trans. Joseph B. Collins (Fort Collins, CO: Roman Catholic Books, 1939), 4.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Goudriaan on Reformed philosophy</title>
		<link>/journal/goudriaan-on-reformed-philosophy/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2016 16:07:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed philosophy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1359</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dr. Aza Goudriaan’s (@Academia) essays are trenchant, weighty, and all-around top shelf in quality. Take, for instance, his foray with Irena Backus on the origin of the term “semipelagianism.”1 Or consider these substantial essays on the role of philosophy in the Reformed orthodox era: &#160; Aza Goudriaan, Reformed Orthodoxy and Philosophy, 1625–1750: Gisbertus Voetius, Petrus &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/goudriaan-on-reformed-philosophy/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Goudriaan on Reformed philosophy"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure id="attachment_1387" style="max-width: 132px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="http://www.godgeleerdheid.vu.nl/nl/over-de-faculteit/medewerkers/wetenschappelijk-personeel-g-l/goudriaan.aspx" rel="attachment wp-att-1387"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Aza_Goudriaan.jpg" alt="Dr. Aza Goudriaan" width="132" height="165" class="size-full wp-image-1387" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Aza Goudriaan</figcaption></figure><a href="https://vu-nl.academia.edu/AzaGoudriaan">Dr. Aza Goudriaan’s</a> <small>(<a href="https://vu-nl.academia.edu/AzaGoudriaan">@Academia</a>)</small> essays are trenchant, weighty, and all-around top shelf in quality. Take, for instance, his foray with Irena Backus on <a href="https://www.academia.edu/5515119/Semipelagianism_The_Origins_of_the_Term_and_its_Passage_into_the_History_of_Heresy">the origin of the term “semipelagianism.”</a><sup id="fnref-1359-1"><a href="#fn-1359-1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Or consider these substantial essays on the role of philosophy in the Reformed orthodox era:</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.brill.com/reformed-orthodoxy-and-philosophy-1625-1750" rel="attachment wp-att-1383"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Goudriaan_ReformedOrthodoxyAndPhilosophy.jpg" alt="Reformed Orthodoxy and Philosophy, 1625–1750: Gisbertus Voetius, Petrus van Mastricht, and Anthonius Driessen — by Aza Goudriaan" width="195" height="292" class="alignright size-full wp-image-1383" /></a> Aza Goudriaan, <a href="http://www.brill.com/reformed-orthodoxy-and-philosophy-1625-1750"><em>Reformed Orthodoxy and Philosophy, 1625–1750: Gisbertus Voetius, Petrus Van Mastricht, and Anthonius Driessen</em></a>, Brill’s Series in Church History 26 (Leiden: Brill, 2006).</li>
<li>Aza Goudriaan, “Ulrik Huber (1636–1694) and John Calvin: The Franeker Debate on Human Reason and the Bible (1686–1687),” <em>Church History and Religious Culture</em> 91, no. 1 (2011): 165–78.</li>
<li>Aza Goudriaan, “Theology and Philosophy,” in <em>A Companion to Reformed Orthodoxy</em>, ed. Herman J. Selderhuis (Leiden: Brill, 2013), 27–63.</li>
</ol>
<p>For whetting one’s appetite, several points in the conclusion of the “Theology and Philosophy” essay are worth considering in the American Reformed and Presbyterian orb. First and foremost:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  Early modem Reformed thinkers did not spurn philosophy in itself. None of the different philosophical orientations articulated during the early modem period seems to have rejected philosophical or natural<br />
  theology as such. In this period there was no such phenomenon as, in the words of a prominent present-day Reformed philosopher, “The Reformed Objection to Natural Theology.” Modern Reformed conceptions, such as those of Barthian theology or of the school of reformational philosophy, differ starkly in their attitude towards natural theology from mainstream seventeenth-century Reformed theology. The latter&#8217;s largely positive reception of proofs for God’s existence clearly demonstrates its evidentialist orientation. <small>(pp. 61–62)</small>
</p></blockquote>
<p>He continues with an observation on the eclecticism of Reformed philosophy in the early modern era, an eclecticism that did not devolve into sheer pluralism and that maintained commitments to biblical authority and the unity of truth in the <em>duplex ordo cognitionis</em><sup id="fnref-1359-2"><a href="#fn-1359-2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  The philosophy that the Reformed adopted was not a single monolithic set of thoughts. Reformed thinkers philosophized in a number of different, sometimes diametrically opposed, ways. Quite a few were Ramists, many opted for an eclectic form of Christian Aristotelianism, while yet others supported Cartesian philosophy and attempted to articulate Reformed theology in terms of Cartesian concepts and presuppositions. Reformed doctrine was obviously taken to be compatible with a number of different philosophical approaches.</p>
<p>  This is not to say that all philosophical orientations were equally compatible with biblical Christianity. In some important respects, Aristotelian eclecticism was able to support biblical exegesis better than Cartesianism was—here one could think of its basic empirical orientation and of the form-matter concepts. The same seems to be true of the Aristotelians’ subordination of natural reason to theology in comparison to the strict separation between theology and philosophy advocated by some Cartesians. It could be argued that the latter separation contributed to a secularization of philosophy which, on the supposition of the unity of truth and its basic knowability, could only lead to an increasing antagonism between philosophy and theology. <small>(p. 62, paragraph break added)</small>
</p></blockquote>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn-1359-1">
Irena Backus and Aza Goudriaan, “‘Semipelagianism’: The Origins of the Term and Its Passage into the History of Heresy,” <em>Journal of Ecclesiastical History</em> 65, no. 1 (2014): 25–46.&#160;<a href="#fnref-1359-1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a>
</li>
<li id="fn-1359-2">
This mouthful of a term, see Richard A. Muller, “‘Duplex Cognitio Dei’ in the Theology of Early Reformed Orthodoxy,” <em>Sixteenth Century Journal</em> 10, no. 2 (Summer 1979): 51–62; Romanus Cessario OP, “<a href="http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_academies/san-tommaso/publications/dc2.pdf#page=53">Duplex Ordo Cognitionis</a>,” Doctor Communis 2 n.s. (2002): 102–9; Eduardo J. Echeverria, <em><a href="http://www.brill.com/berkouwer-and-catholicism">Berkouwer and Catholicism: Disputed Questions</a></em>, Studies in Reformed Theology 24 (Leiden: Brill, 2013).&#160;<a href="#fnref-1359-2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Walgrave on the theology-philosophy relation in Aquinas</title>
		<link>/journal/walgrave-on-the-theology-philosophy-relation-in-aquinas/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2016 23:53:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed orthodoxy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1309</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[J. H. Walgrave, “The Use of Philosophy in the Theology of Thomas Aquinas,” in Aquinas and Problems of His Time, ed. G. Verbeke and D. Verhelst, Mediaevalia Lovaniensia 1 (The Hague: Leuven University Press, 1976), 181–93. Walgrave’s concise and sound explanation of Thomas Aquinas’s view on how theologia sacrae scripturae relates to theologia philosophica, or more broadly faith &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/walgrave-on-the-theology-philosophy-relation-in-aquinas/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Walgrave on the theology-philosophy relation in Aquinas"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan-Baptist_Jozef_Walgrave">J. H. Walgrave</a>, “<a href="https://books.google.be/books?id=Ld-1VEnerwsC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;hl=nl&amp;pg=PA181#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">The Use of Philosophy in the Theology of Thomas Aquinas</a>,” in <i>Aquinas and Problems of His Time</i>, ed. G. Verbeke and D. Verhelst, Mediaevalia Lovaniensia 1 (The Hague: Leuven University Press, 1976), 181–93.</strong></p>
<p>Walgrave’s concise and sound explanation of Thomas Aquinas’s view on how <em>theologia sacrae scripturae</em> relates to <em>theologia philosophica</em>, or more broadly faith to reason, grace to nature, is well worth the perusal. Walgrave focuses his attention on the first of these couplets, elucidating several key passages and principles at play in Aquinas’s thought on this perennial question. More can be said on each of these couplets,<sup id="fnref-1309-1"><a href="#fn-1309-1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> but not less, if, that is, one is to accurately represent the rudiments of Thomas’s position.</p>
<p>To venture a brief historical digression where a lowly American Presbyterian dares to tread on the theology-philosophy-relation question, the patient Protestant reader who is willing to set aside one’s twentieth-century Barthian, Dutch Reformed, Modern Protestant, or otherwise “Christomonistic,” “antithetical,” “anti-scholastic,” and “anti-Hellenization” preconceptions and read Thomas afresh for oneself might be surprised to find not a rationalist, dualistic enemy who, to borrow Walgrave’s phrases, everywhere reduces theology <em>sub metis philosophiae</em> but a champion of faith’s preeminence, a friend of Holy Scripture’s supreme authority, who everywhere reduces philosophy <em>ad metas fidei</em>.</p>
<p>And, to digress further, if one’s Protestant patience were to extend far enough to proceed from perusing the corpus Thomisticum on this perennial question to the 16th- and 17-century Reformed confessional and dogmatic writings on the same, one might be surprised again to find the rudiments of the Thomistic formulations reappearing not infrequently in the writings of the sharpest theological minds within Reformed orthodoxy.</p>
<p>Yet even apart from possible connections into Protestant ressourcement questions, Walgrave’s essay is a worthy companion to the first question in <em>ST</em> and to a fundamental theme in Aquinas’s thought.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn-1309-1">
For example, such sound expansions can be found in Lawrence Dewan, “Faith and Reason from St. Thomas Aquinas’s Perspective,” <em>Science et Esprit</em> 58, no. 2 (May 2006): 113–23; Gerald Van Ackeren SJ, “Reflections on the Relation between Philosophy and Theology,” <em>Theological Studies</em> 14, no. 4 (1953): 527–50.&#160;<a href="#fnref-1309-1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Voetius on metaphysics</title>
		<link>/journal/voetius-on-metaphysics/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 02:33:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed scholasticism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1302</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[&#8230;a theologian is no more able to forego metaphysics and logic than a carpenter a hammer or a soldier weapons. Gisbertus Voetius, Exercitia et bibliotheca studiosi theologiae, 2nd ed. (Utrecht, 1651), 26; cf. Aza Goudriaan, “Theology and Philosophy,” in A Companion to Reformed Orthodoxy, ed. Herman J. Selderhuis (Leiden: Brill, 2013), 27–63 (translation at p. 33; altered). &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/voetius-on-metaphysics/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Voetius on metaphysics"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<figure id="attachment_1306" style="max-width: 150px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="http://www.prdl.org/author_view.php?a_id=68" rel="attachment wp-att-1306"><img class="wp-image-1306 size-thumbnail" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Voetius-150x150.jpg" alt="Gisbertus Voetius (1589–1676)" width="150" height="150" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Gisbertus Voetius (1589–1676)</figcaption></figure>
<p>&#8230;a theologian is no more able to forego metaphysics and logic than a carpenter a hammer or a soldier weapons.</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left; font-size: .8em;">Gisbertus Voetius, <em><a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=KxYVAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA26#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">Exercitia et bibliotheca studiosi theologiae</a></em>, 2nd ed. (Utrecht, 1651), 26; cf. Aza Goudriaan, “Theology and Philosophy,” in <em>A Companion to Reformed Orthodoxy</em>, ed. Herman J. Selderhuis (Leiden: Brill, 2013), 27–63 (translation at p. 33; altered). Full sentence: <em>Ad accuratos, distinctos, &amp; evidentes conceptus tam anascevastice quam catascevastice in Theologia dogmatica &amp; practica, adhaec in explicatione scriptura formandos, ad proprias meditationes ampliandas, &amp; ad alienas diiudicandas non magis metaphysica &amp; logica carere potest Theologus quam faber malleo, aut miles armis.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>“Philosophy should be subject to the measure of faith” — Aquinas</title>
		<link>/journal/philosophy-should-be-subject-to-the-measure-of-faith-aquinas/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2015 16:14:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1234</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[. . . in the use of philosophy in sacred Scripture, there can be a twofold error: In one way, by using doctrines contrary to faith, which are not truths of philosophy, but rather error, or abuse of philosophy, as Origen did. In another way, by using them in such manner as to include under the &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/philosophy-should-be-subject-to-the-measure-of-faith-aquinas/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "“Philosophy should be subject to the measure of faith” — Aquinas"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><a href="//dedeo.tk/tag/thomas-aquinas/"><img class="alignright wp-image-1193 size-medium" style="border: 1px solid black;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Aquinas_Gentile_da_Fabriano1-220x300.jpg" alt="Aquinas_Gentile_da_Fabriano" width="220" height="300" /></a>. . . in the use of philosophy in sacred Scripture, there can be a twofold error:</p>
<p>In one way, by using doctrines contrary to faith, which are not truths of philosophy, but rather error, or abuse of philosophy, as Origen did.</p>
<p>In another way, by using them in such manner as to include under the measure of philosophy truths of faith, as if one should be willing to believe nothing except what could be held by philosophic reasoning; when, on the contrary, philosophy should be subject to the measure of faith, according to the saying of the Apostle (2 Cor. 10:5), “Bringing into captivity every understanding unto the obedience of Christ.”</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: right; font-size: .8em;">— Aquinas, <i>In Boeth. De Trin.</i> <a href="http://www.dhspriory.org/thomas/BoethiusDeTr.htm#23">2.3 <em>responsio</em></a><br />
(trans. by Rose E. Brennan, <i>The Trinity and the Unicity of the Intellect </i>[St. Louis: Herder, 1946]);<br />
cf. Arvin Vos, <em><a href="http://www.worldcat.org/title/aquinas-calvin-and-contemporary-protestant-thought-a-critique-of-protestant-views-on-the-thought-of-thomas-aquinas/oclc/12106146&amp;referer=brief_results">Aquinas, Calvin, and Contemporary Protestant Thought</a> </em>(Grand Rapids: Christian Univ. Press, 1985), ch. 4.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>non sola ratione</title>
		<link>/journal/non-sola-ratione/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 19:41:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1220</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[If the only way open to us for the knowledge of God were solely that of the reason, the human race would remain in the blackest shadows of ignorance. —Aquinas, Cont. Gent. 1.4.4]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><a href="http://dhspriory.org/thomas/english/ContraGentiles1.htm#4"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Aquinas_Gentile_da_Fabriano1-150x150.jpg" alt="Aquinas_Gentile_da_Fabriano" width="150" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-1193" style="border: 1px solid black;"/></a>If the only way open to us for the knowledge of God were solely that of the reason, the human race would remain in the blackest shadows of ignorance.</p></blockquote>
<p style="font-size:.8em;">—Aquinas, <em><a href="http://dhspriory.org/thomas/english/ContraGentiles1.htm#4">Cont. Gent.</em> 1.4.4</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>that other law, the one even sin cannot erase</title>
		<link>/journal/law-one-even-sin-cannot-erase/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2015 17:35:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Augustine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural law]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=861</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Theft is punished by Thy law, O Lord, and the law written in the hearts of men, which iniquity itself effaces not. For what thief will abide a thief? not even a rich thief, one stealing through want. Yet I lusted to thieve, and did it, compelled by no hunger, nor poverty, but through a &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/law-one-even-sin-cannot-erase/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "that other law, the one even sin cannot erase"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Saint_Augustine_by_Philippe_de_Champaigne.jpg"><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-836" style="border: 1px solid black;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Saint_Augustine_by_Philippe_de_Champaigne-239x300.jpg" alt="Saint Augustine by Philippe de Champaigne" width="239" height="300" /></a>Theft is punished by Thy law, O Lord, and the law written in the hearts of men, which iniquity itself effaces not. For what thief will abide a thief? not even a rich thief, one stealing through want. Yet I lusted to thieve, and did it, compelled by no hunger, nor poverty, but through a cloyedness of well-doing, and a pamperedness of iniquity. For I stole that, of which I had enough, and much better. Nor cared I to enjoy what I stole, but joyed in the theft and sin itself.</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: right;">—Augustine, <a href="http://www.ccel.org/ccel/augustine/confess.iii.iv.html"><em>Confessions</em> 2.4</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reformed theology: natural and supernatural</title>
		<link>/journal/reformed-theology-natural-and-supernatural/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2015 10:00:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed scholasticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Synopsis Purioris]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=806</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this locus [i.e., De Sacrosancta Theologia] we restrict Theology only to persons who are proceeding in faith in the current age, and in order to differentiate it, we call it ‘the Theology of revelation.’ Taken more broadly, revelation can be divided into natural and supernatural revelation. We call natural revelation what is either internal, written upon the &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/reformed-theology-natural-and-supernatural/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Reformed theology: natural and supernatural"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><a href="http://www.brill.com/products/book/synopsis-purioris-theologiae-synopsis-purer-theology"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-810" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/SynopsisPurioris.jpg" alt="Synopsis Purioris Theologiae" width="195" height="297" /></a>In this <em>locus</em> [i.e., <em>De Sacrosancta Theologia</em>] we restrict Theology only to persons who are proceeding in faith in the current age, and in order to differentiate it, we call it ‘the Theology of revelation.’</p>
<p>Taken more broadly, revelation can be divided into natural and supernatural revelation.</p>
<p>We call natural revelation what is either internal, written upon the hearts of all people through natural truth and natural law (which the apostle explains in Romans 1:19 and 2:15), or external, through the contemplation of the things God has created (which the same apostle discusses in Romans 1:20). We call supernatural revelation what the prophets and apostles have obtained by the direct agency of the Spirit of truth in order to unfold its genuine form to the Church of God, partly through the spoken word and partly through their writings, and to transmit it for safe-keeping. (<a href="https://archive.org/stream/synopsispurioris00poly#page/2/mode/2up"><em>Synopsis Purioris Theologiae</em></a> 1.6–8)</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: right; font-size: .8em;">—<em><a href="http://www.brill.com/products/book/synopsis-purioris-theologiae-synopsis-purer-theology">Synopsis of a Purer Theology</a>: Latin Text and English Translation</em>, vol. 1, <em>Disputations 1–23</em>,<br />
ed. Dolf te Velde, trans. Riemer A. Faber (Leiden: Brill, 2015), 35.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>theology’s retreat from reality</title>
		<link>/journal/theologys-retreat-reality/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2015 10:00:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith and reason]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=786</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In our own time, it has become the fashion to divorce theology from reason and so to destroy any certitude of its relation to reality. As for the supernatural, well that is an insult to our self-sufficiency not to be lightly suffered by an intelligent man. It is not too hard to understand the modern’s &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/theologys-retreat-reality/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "theology’s retreat from reality"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/WalterFarrell-e1422635050593.jpg"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-784" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/WalterFarrell-e1422635050593.jpg" alt="WalterFarrell" width="200" height="275" /></a>In our own time, it has become the fashion to divorce theology from reason and so to destroy any certitude of its relation to reality. As for the supernatural, well that is an insult to our self-sufficiency not to be lightly suffered by an intelligent man. It is not too hard to understand the modern’s impatience with the supernatural, for man has always been proud; but only the intellectual suicide of positivism could be so absurd as to limit the horizons of man’s mind to what he can uncover by the methods of science.</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: right;">—Fr. Walter Farrell O.P., <a href="http://opcentral.org/sacred-doctrine/"><em>A Companion to the Summa</em></a> (New York: Sheed &amp; Ward, 1945), 11.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
