<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" >

<channel>
	<title>social ethics &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/social-ethics/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Aug 2018 18:23:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9.8</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Calling a spade</title>
		<link>/journal/calling-a-spade/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 21:54:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[morality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophia perennis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1404</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Significant advances can be made along the road of moral reformation by observing the simple expedient of calling a spade a spade. D. Q. McInerny, “Dishonest Language,” in Perennial Wisdom for Daily Life, vol. 1 (Elmhurst, PA: The Priestly Fraternity of Saint Peter, 2002), 6.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>
  Significant advances can be made along the road of moral reformation by observing the simple expedient of calling a spade a spade.
</p></blockquote>
<p>D. Q. McInerny, “Dishonest Language,” in <em>Perennial Wisdom for Daily Life</em>, vol. 1 (Elmhurst, PA: The Priestly Fraternity of Saint Peter, 2002), 6.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>cor legis naturalis</title>
		<link>/journal/cor-legis-naturalis/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 20:11:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theologia naturalis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed orthodoxy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=1353</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[. . . it is imperative for Christians to reaffirm their conviction that God has made the world objectively meaningful and purposeful and that he made human beings capable of discovering this meaning and purpose, despite their sinful propensity to distort what they discover. This, it seems to me, gets to the heart of what, &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/cor-legis-naturalis/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "cor legis naturalis"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>
  . . . it is imperative for Christians to reaffirm their conviction that God has made the world objectively meaningful and purposeful and that he made human beings capable of discovering this meaning and purpose, despite their sinful propensity to distort what they discover. This, it seems to me, gets to the heart of what, historically, Christian natural law theory is all about.</p>
<p>  Natural law, in other words, is not first and foremost a means for making moral or apologetic arguments to which unbelievers will be compelled to give assent, but a means by which Christians express their conviction that God has made this universe in such a manner that there is a morally appropriate way for human beings to live within it, and that, furthermore, the moral law God has explicitly revealed in Scripture is not arbitrary but a reflection of this created reality. The Reformed community’s recent suspicion of natural law theory, I fear, has weakened its theological ability to affirm these things in a coherent and powerful way.
</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: right; font-size:.8em;">— <a href="https://www.wscal.edu/academics/faculty/david-m-vandrunen">David VanDrunen</a>, “Natural Law for Reformed Theology,”<br /><cite>Journal of Reformed Theology</cite> 9, no. 2 (2015): 120.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The either/or that grounds moral judgements</title>
		<link>/journal/tao-moral-judgements/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2015 10:00:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[C. S. Lewis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=823</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We [modern men] have been trying, like Lear, to have it both ways: to lay down our human prerogative and yet at the same time to retain it. It is impossible. Either we are rational spirit obliged for ever to obey the absolute values of the Tao, or else we are mere nature to be &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/tao-moral-judgements/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "The either/or that grounds moral judgements"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C._S._Lewis"><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-816" style="border: 1px solid black;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/CS_Lewis-207x300.jpg" alt="C. S. Lewis (1898–1963)" width="207" height="300" /></a>We [modern men] have been trying, like Lear, to have it both ways: to lay down our human prerogative and yet at the same time to retain it. It is impossible. Either we are rational spirit obliged for ever to obey the absolute values of the <em>Tao</em>, or else we are mere nature to be kneaded and cut into new shapes for the pleasures of masters who must, by hypothesis, have no motive but their own “natural” impulses. Only the <em>Tao</em> provides a common human law of action which can over-arch rulers and ruled alike. A dogmatic belief in objective value is necessary to the very idea of a rule which is not tyranny or an obedience which is not slavery.</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: right; font-size: .8em;">—C. S. Lewis, “<a href="https://archive.org/stream/TheAbolitionOfMan_229/C.s.Lewis-TheAbolitionOfMan#page/n28/mode/1up">The Abolition of Man</a>,” ch. 3 in <em>The Abolition of Man </em>(1943).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Michael West Oborne on the Future of Philosophy and Theology</title>
		<link>/journal/michael-west-oborne-on-the-future-of-philosophy-and-theology/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2014 13:46:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Protestantism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dedeo.tk/?p=553</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dr. Michael West Oborne’s recent graduation address at the Dominican School of Philosophy &#38; Theology, “Philosophy and Theology’s Role in Meeting Tomorrow’s Public Policy Challenges” (Vimeo), is worth pondering in its own right. Additionally, for us Protestants who are engaged in conversation on the future of Protestantism, Oborne’s pursuit of “strategic foresight” into how the global socio-political landscape will &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/michael-west-oborne-on-the-future-of-philosophy-and-theology/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Michael West Oborne on the Future of Philosophy and Theology"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.dspt.edu/Page/574"><img class="alignright wp-image-557 size-full" style="border: 1px solid black;" src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/MichaelOborne.jpg" alt="Dr. Michael West Oborne" width="194" height="259" /></a><a title="Read Dr. Oborne’s bio at the Dominican School of Philosophy and Theology" href="http://www.dspt.edu/Page/574">Dr. Michael West Oborne’s</a> recent graduation address at the Dominican School of Philosophy &amp; Theology, “<a title="The video and transcript of Dr. Oborne’s address are available at the Dominican School of Philosophy and Theology" href="http://www.dspt.edu/Page/575">Philosophy and Theology’s Role in Meeting Tomorrow’s Public Policy Challenges</a>” (<a title="Watch the address at Vimeo." href="http://vimeo.com/98412573">Vimeo</a>), is worth pondering in its own right.</p>
<p>Additionally, for us Protestants who are engaged in conversation on <a href="http://www.davenanttrust.org/projects/the-future-of-protestantism/">the future of Protestantism</a>, Oborne’s pursuit of “strategic foresight” into how the global socio-political landscape will be changing over the coming decades opens a powerful and perhaps underappreciated perspective vista in Protestant dialog. Like it or not the world is changing significantly and undeniably in the areas Oborne highlights:</p>
<blockquote><p>demographics, climate change adaptation, increased integration and sophistication of technologies, the balance between public and private economic markets, resource availability and management, sustainable economic growth, equity and wealth distribution, the future of meaningful jobs and employment, geopolitical transformations, and the rule of law in societies.</p></blockquote>
<p>To take just one example:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #000000;">According to current projections, the global population will reach eight billion by 2030, and will likely reach around nine billion by 2050. In other words, the global population is projected to grow nearly 30% in the next forty years.</span></p></blockquote>
<p>According to Oborne, the socio-political effects of such growth, together with globalization, disruptive technological and biological developments and all the rest, will be drastic everywhere and will require deep rooting in philosophical and theological fundamentals in order to navigate the universal constant that will animate and dominate tomorrow’s public discourse: <em>change</em>.</p>
<p>Whether Protestants are, first, aware of such shifts and, second, producing men and women capable of navigating these tumultuous seas with a moral compass oriented toward their source and “chief and highest end” (WLC 1) are questions that need to be added to Protestant conversations on its future.</p>
<p>Further, to press deeper here and inquire a bit into the foundations of Protestant discourse, is there something valuable to be appropriated in the manner by which the Dominican tradition poses the question of tomorrow: theology <em>and philosophy’s</em> role? Is it the case that we Protestants know a thing or two about “political theology” but could learn a thing or two about political <em>philosophy </em>and another thing or two about the interrelation of faith and reason, especially in relation to social ethics and the common good?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>prima gratia and that which is prior to moral argument</title>
		<link>/journal/prima-gratia-prior-moral-argument/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2013 14:21:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=432</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When the Pope’s commission of moral theologians argued for the priority of a human dominion in which human practical reason supplies the concrete norms, or when the Supreme Court declared in Casey that the individual has natural immunity from positive law in the matter of abortion, it is important to understand that these are not moral &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/prima-gratia-prior-moral-argument/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "prima gratia and that which is prior to moral argument"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><a href="http://www.worldcat.org/title/first-grace-rediscovering-the-natural-law-in-a-post-christian-world/oclc/51310560&amp;referer=brief_results"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-435" style="margin-left: 10px; border: 1px solid black;" alt="Russell Hittinger, The First Grace: Rediscovering the Natural Law in a Post-Christian World" src="https://dash.dedeo.tk/wp-content/uploads/Hittinger_TheFirstGrace.jpg" width="140" height="208" /></a>When the Pope’s commission of moral theologians argued for the priority of a human dominion in which human practical reason supplies the concrete norms, or when the Supreme Court declared in <em>Casey</em> that the individual has natural immunity from positive law in the matter of abortion, it is important to understand that these are not moral arguments but claims about what is prior to arguments. The Answer to this question is entire relevant to morals, but nothing in the logic of moral argument <em>per se</em> can win the case. The question turns upon considerations of anthropology and theology. To attempt to rediscover the natural law in a post-Christian world we must pick up the discussion precisely at this point.</p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: right;">—Russell Hittinger, introduction to <a href="http://www.worldcat.org/title/first-grace-rediscovering-the-natural-law-in-a-post-christian-world/oclc/51310560&amp;referer=brief_results"><em>The First Grace</em></a>, xlvi.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>“Do Not Quarrel on the Way”: a sermon on Genesis 45:24</title>
		<link>/journal/quarrel-way-sermon-genesis-4524/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2013 04:06:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Sermons]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[anger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Decalogue]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genesis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[murder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Westminster Larger Catechism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=420</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Recently I preached on what at first glance seems like a throw-away line in the climactic reunion scene of the Joseph story: “do not quarrel on the way.” This is the last thing that Joseph says to his brothers before he sends them back to Canaan for the second time, and it only makes sense if &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/quarrel-way-sermon-genesis-4524/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "“Do Not Quarrel on the Way”: a sermon on Genesis 45:24"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Giovanni_Andrea_de_Ferrari_-_%27Joseph%27s_Coat_Brought_to_Jacob%27,_oil_on_canvas,_c._1640,_El_Paso_Museum_of_Art.jpg"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-421" style="margin-left: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; border: 1px solid black;" title="Giovanni Andrea de Ferrari — Joseph's Coat brought to Jacob" alt="Giovanni Andrea de Ferrari — Joseph's Coat brought to Jacob" src="https://dash.dedeo.tk/wp-content/uploads/Giovanni_Andrea_de_Ferrari—Josephs_Coat.jpg" width="279" height="240" /></a></p>
<p>Recently I preached on what at first glance seems like a throw-away line in the climactic reunion scene of the Joseph story: “do not quarrel on the way.” This is the last thing that Joseph says to his brothers before he sends them back to Canaan for the <em>second</em> time, and it only makes sense if you put it in the context of the dramatic transition from murderous hatred in the opening scenes to reconciliation and brotherly love in the climax.</p>
<p>Despite its brevity and enigmatic character, I find the importance of this command—both for Joseph’s brothers and for contemporary life—to lie in its relation to the sixth commandment. Consider, for instance, how the Larger Catechism explains the duties and prohibitions of this commandment in line with Jesus’s teaching on anger in Matthew 5.</p>
<blockquote><p>Q. 134. Which is the sixth commandment?<br />
A. The sixth commandment is, Thou shalt not kill.</p>
<p>Q. 135. What are the duties required in the sixth commandment?<br />
A. The duties required in the sixth commandment are, all careful studies, and lawful endeavors, to preserve the life of ourselves and others by resisting all thoughts and purposes, subduing all passions, and avoiding all occasions, temptations, and practices, which tend to the unjust taking away the life of any; by just defense thereof against violence, patient bearing of the hand of God, quietness of mind, cheerfulness of spirit; a sober use of meat, drink, physic, sleep, labor, and recreations; by charitable thoughts, love, compassion, meekness, gentleness, kindness; peaceable, mild and courteous speeches and behavior; forbearance, readiness to be reconciled, patient bearing and forgiving of injuries, and requiting good for evil; comforting and succoring the distressed, and protecting and defending the innocent.</p>
<p>Q. 136. What are the sins forbidden in the sixth commandment?<br />
A. The sins forbidden in the sixth commandment are, all taking away the life of ourselves, or of others, except in case of public justice, lawful war, or necessary defense; the neglecting or withdrawing the lawful and necessary means of preservation of life; sinful anger, hatred, envy, desire of revenge; all excessive passions, distracting cares; immoderate use of meat, drink, labor, and recreations; provoking words, oppression, quarreling, striking, wounding, and whatsoever else tends to the destruction of the life of any.</p></blockquote>
<p>There is likely no message needed more in our quarrelsome and bloodthirsty times—both within and without the church—than demanding brotherly unity as a means of fostering human flourishing. And there is likely no moral imperative that blatantly reveals our moral failures as humans and clearly shows us our need for the Father’s love, Christ’s mediation, and the Holy Spirit’s powerful indwelling than that which Joseph commands his brothers.</p>
<audio class="wp-audio-shortcode" id="audio-420-2" preload="none" style="width: 100%;" controls="controls"><source type="audio/mpeg" src="http://ia601004.us.archive.org/12/items/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.mp3?_=2" /><a href="http://ia601004.us.archive.org/12/items/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.mp3">http://ia601004.us.archive.org/12/items/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.mp3</a></audio>
<p>(download: <a href="http://archive.org/download/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.mp3">MP3</a>; <a href="http://archive.org/download/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.ogg">OGG</a>; <a href="http://archive.org/download/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.4">FLAC</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	<enclosure url="http://ia601004.us.archive.org/12/items/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.mp3" length="57111552" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="http://archive.org/download/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.mp3" length="0" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="http://archive.org/download/Genesis451464--DoNotQuarrelOnTheWay/ODONNELL_13OCT2013_Gen45_46.ogg" length="0" type="audio/ogg" />
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bavinckiana digitalia: A Review Essay</title>
		<link>/journal/bavinckiana-digitalia-review-essay/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2013 16:06:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dogmatics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Herman Bavinck]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=405</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Laurence O’Donnell, Bavinckiana digitalia: A Review Essay, The Bavinck Review 4 (2013): 51–63. In this essay I present the state of the art concerning digital tools for Bavinck studies. I wrote this primarily for two groups of Bavinck scholars: first, the ever-growing number of non-European and non-American readers who might not have immediate access to digital &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/bavinckiana-digitalia-review-essay/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Bavinckiana digitalia: A Review Essay"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://bavinckinstitute.org/review/tbr-4-2013/"><img class="alignright wp-image-406 size-full" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/TBR4_cover.jpg" alt="The Bavinck Review, vol. 4" width="200" height="300" /></a> Laurence O’Donnell, <a href="http://bavinckinstitute.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/TBR4_05_ODonnell.pdf"><em>Bavinckiana digitalia</em>: A Review Essay</a>, <em>The Bavinck Review</em> 4 (2013): 51–63.</p>
<p>In this essay I present the state of the art concerning digital tools for Bavinck studies. I wrote this primarily for two groups of Bavinck scholars: first, the ever-growing number of non-European and non-American readers who might not have immediate access to digital media developed primarily in the West; second, the scholar for whom digital media is not his or her forte but who wishes nevertheless to know what sort of tools are currently available. Additionally, I hope that these reflections spur further development both in software development and in academic institutional development related to Bavinck studies. I suggest that the Bavinck Institute (or, as other have suggested, worldwide Bavinck Institutes) might benefit from modeling its digitization efforts after similar initiatives such as the <a href="http://kuyper.ptsem.edu/">Kuyper Digital Library</a> and the <a href="http://www.ccel.org/">CCEL</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Saudi Domestic Abuse Law</title>
		<link>/journal/saudi-domestic-abuse-law/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2013 17:26:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sharia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=316</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Saudi Arabia’s new domestic abuse law (reported by Al Jazeera and thoughtfully commented on at Tabsir), the result of the No More Abuse campaign, is noteworthy in several respects. To pick just one, in such adjustments to positive law in Islamic societies wherein Sharia regulations are “improved,” “modernized,” and/or sidestepped, is this the result of classical &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/saudi-domestic-abuse-law/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Saudi Domestic Abuse Law"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-317" alt="No More Abuse Campaign" src="https://dash.dedeo.tk/wp-content/uploads/NoMoreAbuse.jpg" width="225" height="171" /></p>
<p>Saudi Arabia’s new domestic abuse law (reported by <a href="http://america.aljazeera.com/articles/2013/8/30/saudi-arabia-passeslawcriminalizingdomesticabuse.html">Al Jazeera</a> and thoughtfully commented on <a href="http://tabsir.net/?p=2219">at Tabsir</a>), the result of the <a href="http://www.kkfeng.org/no-more-abuse.php">No More Abuse</a> campaign, is noteworthy in several respects. To pick just one, in such adjustments to positive law in Islamic societies wherein Sharia regulations are “improved,” “modernized,” and/or sidestepped, is this the result of classical natural-law-style conceptions of justice prevailing over outmoded formulations of divine law; or, is this simply the inevitable march of modern Enlightenment poking its toes into the Kingdom’s waters?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pope Francis’s Message to Muslims</title>
		<link>/journal/pope-franciss-message-to-muslims/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2013 12:10:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian-Muslim relations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=260</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Pope Francis’s brief message to Muslims in celebration of Eid al-Fitr is worth a read. Politically speaking, it is interesting to note the Pope’s likely intentionally distancing himself from the perceived foibles of his predecessor’s attempts at interacting with Muslims. (Cf. “Pope Sends Message of Respect for Muslims,” New York Times, 2 August 2013.) And perhaps he &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/pope-franciss-message-to-muslims/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Pope Francis’s Message to Muslims"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-263" alt="Pope Francis" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/PopeFrancis.jpg" width="200" height="249" /></p>
<p><a href="http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/francesco/messages/pont-messages/2013/documents/papa-francesco_20130710_musulmani-ramadan_en.html">Pope Francis’s brief message to Muslims</a> in celebration of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eid_al-Fitr">Eid al-Fitr</a> is worth a read.</p>
<p>Politically speaking, it is interesting to note the Pope’s likely intentionally distancing himself from the perceived foibles of his predecessor’s attempts at interacting with Muslims. (Cf. “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/08/03/world/europe/pope-sends-message-of-respect-for-muslims.html?_r=0">Pope Sends Message of Respect for Muslims</a>,” New York Times, 2 August 2013.) And perhaps he is taking a page out of President Obama’s playbook in getting out of the gate early with positive overtures to Muslim leaders.</p>
<p>Religously speaking, we Protestants who care about Christian-Muslim relations would do well to consider the virtue themes underlying the Pope’s message of mutual respect regarding education. One passage in particular is worthy of honest reflection especially for those of us who have been influenced by the neo-Calvinist tradition with its penchant for calling down fires of antithesis not only upon adherents of others religions but also upon fellow Christians who do not agree with us on secondary and tertiary matters of faith and/or practice and who have no small amount of making up to do in the love thy neighbor as thyself department:</p>
<blockquote><p>It is clear that, when we show respect for the religion of our neighbours or when we offer them our good wishes on the occasion of a religious celebration, we simply seek to share their joy, without making reference to the content of their religious convictions.</p></blockquote>
<p>There is an important distinction at play here: the ability of a believer of religion A to share in the joy of a religious celebration for believer of religion B without believer A condoning the religious convictions of believer B or, by implication, forfeiting the truth claims of religion A in order to share in the joyous event sponsored by religion B. In other words, for a Christian, loving one’s Muslim neighbor as one’s self does not entail the removal of all religious distinctions, but it does entail a mutual commitment to basic human virtues such as respect for the other, specifically his person and his religion. Hence the Pope’s Eid well wishes do not mean that he is mixing the Meccan religion with the Roman.</p>
<p>Certainly one distinction does not world peace make. Nevertheless, for Christians courageous enough to pursue the path of social-ethical virtue <em>with</em> the other, Pope Francis’s distinction provides an important roadsign on the path of peace. Not only the streets of Egypt and Iraq but also the streets of my fair city—sunny Orlando—need such virtue now more than ever.</p>
<p>It is always easier to thank God that I am not like the other than to love the other as myself. Christians, more than any other people, ought to be the first to choose the higher way, the way of love that patiently bears with the other.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>An excellent review of Bratt’s new biography of Kuyper</title>
		<link>/journal/an-excellent-review-of-bratts-new-biography-of-kuyper/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2013 18:50:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Abraham Kuyper]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[neo-Calvinism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=234</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Davey Hendrickson wrote an excellent review of Professor Bratt’s new biography of Abraham Kuyper.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Davey Hendrickson <a href="http://www.cardus.ca/comment/article/4000/can-these-bones-live-unexpected-lessons-from-the-life-of-kuyper/">wrote an excellent review</a> of Professor Bratt’s new biography of Abraham Kuyper.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
