<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" >

<channel>
	<title>two kingdoms &#8211; de Deo</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/journal/tag/two-kingdoms/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>“In Thy light we see light”</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Aug 2018 18:23:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9.8</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Free download: Johannes van Oort, Jerusalem and Babylon: A Study of Augustine’s City of God and the Sources of His Doctrine of the Two Cities (Leiden: Brill, 2013)</title>
		<link>/journal/free-download-johannes-van-oort-jerusalem-and-babylon-a-study-of-augustines-city-of-god-and-the-sources-of-his-doctrine-of-the-two-cities-leiden-brill-2013/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 14:42:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dies und Das]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacra doctrina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Augustine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[two kingdoms]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=922</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Johannes van Oort, Jerusalem and Babylon: A Study of Augustine’s City of God and the Sources of His Doctrine of the Two Cities (Leiden: Brill, 2013).]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Johannes van Oort, <a href="https://www.academia.edu/4535739/Book_Freely_Available_2013_Jerusalem_and_Babylon_A_Study_of_Augustines_City_of_God_and_the_Sources_of_his_Doctrine_of_the_Two_Cities"><em>Jerusalem and Babylon: A Study of Augustine’s</em> City of God <em>and the Sources of His Doctrine of the Two Cities</em></a> (Leiden: Brill, 2013).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Natural law theory’s Herculean project</title>
		<link>/journal/natural-law-theorys-herculean-project/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 15:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lo]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[two kingdoms]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dedeo.tk/?p=199</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Classical natural law theory presupposes classical metaphysics. Hence, first: [D]efending natural law and natural theology requires revitalizing the entire classical metaphysical tradition and attacking the metaphysical assumptions of modern philosophy at their core. And second: We “old” natural law theorists, meanwhile, do appeal to “inherent purposes” and “nature’s forms.”  We agree with Hart that natural law theory requires &#8230; <p class="link-more"><a href="/journal/natural-law-theorys-herculean-project/" class="more-link">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Natural law theory’s Herculean project"</span></a></p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://edwardfeser.blogspot.com/2013/07/hart-stopping.html"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-201" alt="Hercules" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Hercules1.jpg" width="251" height="323" /></a>Classical natural law theory presupposes classical metaphysics. Hence, first:</p>
<blockquote><p>[D]efending natural law and natural theology requires revitalizing the entire classical metaphysical tradition and attacking the metaphysical assumptions of modern philosophy at their core.</p></blockquote>
<p>And second:</p>
<blockquote><p>We “old” natural law theorists, meanwhile, do appeal to “inherent purposes” and “nature’s forms.”  We agree with Hart that natural law theory requires such a classical metaphysical foundation.  But precisely for that reason, we are also well aware that that entails that we are committed to a radically different conception of nature from that of modern secularists, and that “any ‘natural’ terms [we] employ have very different meanings for [those] interlocutors” (as Hart tells us — as if it were news).  We realize that we cannot take for granted a common metaphysical understanding of the natural world and proceed directly to moral arguments, but have first to challenge the moderns’ understanding of nature itself, and that this is a Herculean project.</p></blockquote>
<p>—Dr. Edward Feser, “<a href="http://edwardfeser.blogspot.com/2013/07/hart-stopping.html">Hart stopping</a>”</p>
<p>I highlight this classically Roman Catholic assumption not to enter into the Hart-Feser debate on natural law in <em>First Things</em> and elsewhere (Feser links to the salvos in the first paragraph of his “<a href="http://edwardfeser.blogspot.com/2013/07/hart-stopping.html">Hart stopping</a>”) but to pause for a brief reflection on the interrelation of natural law and metaphysics in natural law discussions in the NAPARC world: is this same philosophical assumption valid and necessary in Protestant natural law theory?</p>
<p>A few pointed sub-questions lend themselves to further reflection on this point:</p>
<ul>
<li>Can the Reformed tradition revitalize its natural law heritage without “revitalizing the entire classical metaphysical tradition”?</li>
<li>Can the Reformed tradition continue to castigate, ignore, or otherwise downplay the other correlate of natural law besides the much-discussed <em>duplex regnum—</em>natural theology—and at the same time recover natural law theory?</li>
<li>Would Reformed theologians—who would readily affirm a “radically different conception of nature from that of modern secularists”—also affirm that “that natural law theory requires . . . a classical metaphysical foundation”?</li>
<li>Are Reformed theologians content to deduce an entire theory of natural law from scriptural proof texts such as Romans 2:14–15, or would they affirm the need “first to challenge the moderns’ understanding of nature itself” and second “that this is a Herculean project”?</li>
<li>Supposing that the parties in the NAPARC discussions of natural law (whether proponents or opponents) affirm “that this is a Herculean project,” would they hold that this is a philosophical or a theological project? To use the older language: which science in the encyclopedia of the sciences would they task with tackling this project?</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
